<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Francis Terry and Associates</title>
    <description>Francis Terry and Associates are designers of new-build and restorations of classical Georgian style architecture and country houses
</description>
    <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ftanda.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 02:19:11 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 02:19:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/hans-place-12-24.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/hans-place-12-24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to be part of a team which have been granted planning consent for a new seven unit apartment scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge. The new building replaces a modernist style house built in the 1960s, which is unsympathetic to the area both in terms of materials and architectural language. The new design follows the dominant style of the square which consists of highly ornate red brick facades with brown stone and terracotta elements, using a classical style borrowed from diverse sources, including 17th century Dutch and Queen Anne influences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/hans-place-12-24-3.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/hans-place-12-24-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/hans-place-12-24-2.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/hans-place-12-24-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-hans-place-knightsbridge/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-hans-place-knightsbridge/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Planning Permission Granted for a New House in Surrey</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/house-surrey-11-24.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Planning Permission Granted for a New House in Surrey&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/house-surrey-11-24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning Permission Granted for a New House in Surrey&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are delighted that our design for a new house in Surrey has been given planning permission by Waverley Borough Council. The design reflects local architectural characteristics with the use of stone and red brick, with a clay tile roof. The architectural detailing owes much to the Surrey vernacular and the work of Sir Edwin Lutyens who practiced extensively in the area. The planning submission was coordinated by Janet Long of Planit Consulting and the landscape design was by Nick Tripp of Taylor Tripp.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-house-surrey/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-house-surrey/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Planning Permission Granted for a New House in Hampshire</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/house-hampshire-11-24.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Planning Permission Granted for a New House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/house-hampshire-11-24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning Permission Granted for a New House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are delighted that our design for a new house in Hampshire has been given planning permission by South Downs National Park Authority (SDNPA). This scheme is particularly exciting as the site was originally laid out by Charles Bridgeman, one of the greatest English landscape designers of the 18th century. The house is designed in the classical style but subtly adapted to fulfil the functional requirements of modern family life. The materials used include brick, stone and flint which reflect local architectural character. The scheme was project managed by Finchatton, the landscape designer was Christian Sweet of Coulson Stone, and the planning consultant was Scot Masker of Masker Architects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-house-hampshire-2024/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-house-hampshire-2024/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Francis Terry’s Scheme for the Roman Circus in Colchester</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/roman-circus-10-24.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Francis Terry’s Scheme for the Roman Circus in Colchester&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/roman-circus-10-24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Francis Terry’s Scheme for the Roman Circus in Colchester&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Roman chariot racing track (circus) was recently discovered to the south of Colchester city centre. This had gone unnoticed for nearly two thousand years because no actual building material was above ground. It is the only one of its kind in northern Europe and bears witness to the huge significance of Colchester during Roman times. To celebrate this discovery, Francis Terry has designed a proposal to surround the original racetrack with terraced housing and rebuild the original starting gates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/roman-circus-2-10-24.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Francis Terry’s Scheme for the Roman Circus in Colchester&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/roman-circus-2-10-24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Francis Terry’s Scheme for the Roman Circus in Colchester&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are his thoughts on the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago, a Roman chariot racing track was discovered to the south of Colchester city centre. This had gone unnoticed for nearly two thousand years because no actual building material was above ground. Following the end of the Roman occupation of Britain, stone and brick from the site was taken and reused for building Medieval Colchester. The result is that virtually no material remains on the site at all, even much of the foundations have been removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its day this would have been a structure of national importance, perhaps the only one of its type in the country. Constructed in around 125AD, possibly under the orders of Emperor Hadrian, who was the man responsible for some of the most celebrated works of architecture of all history including, the Pantheon, Castel Sant’ Angelo and Hadrian’s Villa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I became interested in this site back in 2010 when I joined a campaign to buy the Sergeants Mess which sits at the west end of the circus. It was felt that this would make an excellent visitors’ centre as it would have the site of the starting gates within its garden. Unfortunately, this did not happen due to lack of funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I revisited the site in 2023 and saw the current interpretation of the starting gates which consists of ten recently built brick piers, all about 3 ft high, which show the position of where the starting gates once were. Though I salute the effort in creating these brick and stone piers, they have not gone far enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then thought of the simple idea of rebuilding the starting gates in their entirety, in their original position using the same materials the Romans used and the same construction method. As a classical architect I am familiar with Roman construction, rules of classical proportion and the practical use of load bearing brick and stone structures. So, I drew out what I imagined the starting gates would look like. With my experience and knowledge of Roman architecture I came up with a plausible design. This was no great work of genius as loadbearing masonry construction with the use of brick and stone, the design becomes the inevitable consequence of these factors. I can be very sure the starting gates look similar to this, although there is no record of their structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these drawings I asked a stone mason to provide a price to carry out the work. He came back with a detailed breakdown which put the price at £2 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now in the position of trying to get the necessary funds to start the rebuilding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that this venture is hugely important to the future of Colchester. With the problems facing town and city centres with shopping going online, the built heritage becomes increasingly important to keep these places vibrant and active. We have an opportunity to give both locals and tourists something to celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Germany flattened Warsaw during the war, the attitude was to rebuild it as close as possible to what it had been. Where photographic evidence was missing, they used the 18th century paintings of Bernardo Bellotto to fill the gaps and, at times improve what had been. This creative rebuilding programme was an important act to give the people of Warsaw a feeling of belonging and civic pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colchester was a town of immense importance during the Roman period. It was to Colchester that the Emperor Claudius came all the way from Rome (possibly on Elephants) to receive the surrender of the British tribal chiefs. At the time of Vesuvius’s eruption, the population of Pompeii was 10 to 20,000, Colchester at its height had a population of 30,000. It is an understatement that the significance of this history is not matched by what can be seen of Roman Colchester. My hope is that by rebuilding the starting gates, a unique Roman monument can be revived, and I look forward to seeing the great benefits which will come from this endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/roman-circus-3-10-24.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Francis Terry’s Scheme for the Roman Circus in Colchester&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/roman-circus-3-10-24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Francis Terry’s Scheme for the Roman Circus in Colchester&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea has attached much press attention as can be seen by the following links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gazette-news.co.uk/news/24625420.architect-wants-celebrate-colchesters-roman-history/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollower noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; alt=&quot;Architect wants to 'celebrate' Colchester's Roman history&quot; title=&quot;Architect wants to 'celebrate' Colchester's Roman history&quot;&gt;Architect wants to ‘celebrate’ Colchester’s Roman history&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Gazette)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gazette-news.co.uk/news/24513968.colchesters-roman-circus-gates-rebuilt-1-4m/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollower noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; alt=&quot;Colchester's Roman circus gates could be rebuilt for £1.4m&quot; title=&quot;Colchester's Roman circus gates could be rebuilt for £1.4m&quot;&gt;Colchester’s Roman circus gates could be rebuilt for £1.4m&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Gazette)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gazette-news.co.uk/news/24652020.colchester-council-will-debate-housing-roman-circus-site/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollower noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; alt=&quot;Colchester Council will debate housing on Roman Circus site&quot; title=&quot;Colchester Council will debate housing on Roman Circus site&quot;&gt;Colchester Council will debate housing on Roman Circus site&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;(Gazette)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/roman-circus/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/roman-circus/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>M&amp;S Flagship Store Demolition Alternative Proposal</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/02-m-and-s-01.jpg&quot; title=&quot;M&amp;amp;S Flagship Store Demolition Alternative Proposal&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/02-m-and-s-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;M&amp;amp;S Flagship Store Demolition Alternative Proposal&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis Terry in collaboration with Create Streets have designed an alternative proposal to the Marks &amp;amp; Spencer’s proposed total demolition of their historic store in Oxford Street. Robert Kwolek has written about it in The Sunday Times here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marks and Spencer’s proposal to demolish their 1930 Oxford Street flagship store (Orchard House) has proved very controversial with a government call in, an appeal to the High Court and high-profile interventions from (among others) Kevin McCloud, Griff Rhys Jones, Sir Simon Jenkins and Kristin Scott Thomas as well as a host of experts from the worlds of architecture, heritage and planning. It has served as a prominent cause célèbre for important interrelated debates about net zero development, the future of department stores, twentieth century heritage and high streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future for Orchard House is once more in doubt following the March 2024 High Court decision. The Secretary of State had turned down the planning application, but the High Court has upheld a judicial review of the rejected planning permission. The only grounds on which the Secretary of State’s refusal was not overturned was his approach to the store’s sensitive heritage setting. However, this is not the end of the story. The Secretary of State now needs to redetermine the appeal. He could, in theory, still refuse planning permission. What will the Secretary of State, whomever that may be, do after the general election?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more sustainable and better path is possible. Trade offs are inevitable between the viability of the site, its heritage, its uses, its embodied carbon, ongoing sustainability and the quality, beauty and future of Oxford Street. Nevertheless, Create Streets believes that an approach which sought to reuse more of the existing building and was less dismissive of the existing setting would have been wiser, less costly for Marks and Spencer and more popular with the wider public. Working with the internationally significant classical architect, Francis Terry, we have therefore worked up an alternative proposal which;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;text-list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Creates a comparable volume of overall development to ensure viability&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Could be built to a broadly comparable cost&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Accepts some demolition whilst saving what can be saved&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Encloses the street more fittingly and elegantly to Oxford Street’s long-term benefit&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Creates an improved new public space at Granville Place&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Creates elegant public arcades through the site&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Creates a development in which it would be possible to create homes as well as offices and shops&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Creates a better street with a raised crossing and street trees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach is much more popular with the general public and this something we can agree on. In a national opinion poll conducted by Deltapoll in February 2024,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;text-list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The British public overwhelmingly preferred our design by 79 per cent to 17 per cent&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;This preference transcends politics. Voters for all three main British parties strongly preferred our design with Liberal Democrat voters being closest to the national average (80 vs 15 per cent for Liberal Democrat voters; 76 vs 20 per cent for Labour voters and 83 vs 14 per cent for Conservative voters)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;This preference transcends views on Europe. Views on the design from “remain” and “leave” voters were almost identical. (80 vs 15 per cent for “remain” voters and 80 vs 17 per cent for “leave” voters)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A preference that is shared by rich and poor. Those of ABC1 social status and of C2DE social status both strongly prefer our design. (82 vs. 15 per cent for ABC1 and 75 vs. 21 per cent for C2DE)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A preference that is shared everywhere. Respondents in every British region strongly preferred our design with the highest support in the South of England (83 vs. 13 per cent) and Scotland (83 per cent vs 15 per cent) and the lowest in Wales (71 vs 26 per cent)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A preference of old and young. Clear majorities of all age groups preferred our design though with support slightly increasing with age. (75 vs 23 per cent for those aged 18-24 and 83 vs. 12 per cent for those aged over 65)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.createstreets.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/OrchardHouse_110624.pdf&quot; alt=&quot;Orchard House Saved?&quot; rel=&quot;noreply noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Read the full report here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thetimes.com/life-style/property-home/article/marks-and-spencers-oxford-street-battle-ask-the-public-what-they-think-xmjxf0crr&quot; alt=&quot;Marks &amp;amp; Spencer’s Oxford Street battle? Ask the public what they think&quot; rel=&quot;noreply noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Read The Sunday Times article here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.createstreets.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/RK-on-GB-News-180624-1.mp4&quot; alt=&quot;Make Britain Beautiful Again&quot; rel=&quot;noreply noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Watch Robert Kwolek’s interview on GB News here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/m-and-s-flagship-store-demolition-alternative-proposal/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/m-and-s-flagship-store-demolition-alternative-proposal/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Planning Permission Granted for a New House Within the Blenheim Estate</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/blenheim-estate-06-24.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Planning Permission Granted for a New House Within the Blenheim Estate&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/blenheim-estate-06-24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning Permission Granted for a New House Within the Blenheim Estate&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are delighted that our new house in the grounds of Blenheim Palace has been granted planning permission. This is a particularly prestigious consent as the house is within a Grade 1 listed landscape and on a UNESCO World Heritage Site. The standard required by UNESCO, Historic England and West Oxford District Council is understandably of the highest level. We are therefore honoured to be the architects for such a significant consent. The Country House expert Jeremy Musson commended the design in the following way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
	“The proposed house will become the comfortable and elegant centrepiece of an enclosed and inhabited grove within the wider story of Blenheim – another chapter in the unfolding Marlborough/Spencer-Churchill story and is designed as the permanent and future residence of the Marquis and Marchioness of Blandford, their family and successors.”
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-house-blenheim-estate/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-house-blenheim-estate/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>NPPF Paragraph 84e Explained</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;videoWrapper&quot;&gt;
	&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/e1OGitGRWj0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people, perhaps you, would love to build yourself a new house in the country where you could live with your family and work from home in rural tranquility. It is perhaps the English dream. The problem is getting planning permission. But don’t despair, NPPF paragraph 84e is the planning legislation which is specifically written to allow this to happen. The clause states that the new house has to be an ‘exceptional’ work of architecture and so it is not easy to get planning permission… but not impossible. In this video architect Francis Terry and planning specialist Martin Leay discuss how this can be done in practical terms using examples of their many past successes of ‘paragraph 84e’ houses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;francis-terry&quot;&gt;Francis Terry&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/nppf-paragraph-84e-explained/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/nppf-paragraph-84e-explained/</guid>
        
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
        <category>videos</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Planning Permission Granted for a New House in Hampshire</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2023/house-hampshire-09-23.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Planning Permission Granted for a New House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2023/thumbs/house-hampshire-09-23.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning Permission Granted for a New House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are happy to hear that our design for a new house in Hampshire has been given planning permission by East Hampshire District Council. The design reflects local architectural characteristics, with the use of red brick, weatherboarding, clay tile roofing and traditional vernacular details. The scheme was commissioned and project managed by Finchatton and the landscape designer was Christian Sweet of Coulson Stone, both of whom we work with frequently and continue to collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-house-hampshire/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-house-hampshire/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why does my Puppy like Mozart?</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/01a.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/sociala.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Why does my Puppy like Mozart?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	We recently bought a puppy and discovered that he much prefers classical music to pop. You might think that I have brainwashed our new pet, but we only had him a few days when I discovered this, and most of the music played in our house is instigated by my teenage children whose taste is decidedly unclassical. I am not alone in this discovery; after a short amount of research I found that numerous studies revealed dogs like some types of music and not others. One such piece of research showed that shelter dogs were found to be more relaxed and quieter when they were listening to classical music and barked more when heavy metal was playing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	From this it seems that dogs are born with discernible musical tastes which effects their moods and this seems to be consistent throughout the species. It would be interesting to know whether similar generalisation can be applied to humans. Certainly, artists as great as Bach or Mozart seem to transcend all cultural barriers and studies have shown that their music has a therapeutic effect. Classical music has been successful piped into crime ridden areas to reduce the instances of violence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Various types of music certainly produce particular moods in us - it would be interesting to know which types of architecture affect us in in different ways. Architecture does affect your moods, a brutalist housing development will put you in a different frame of mind to Renaissance church or Rococo boudoir. It would be amazing to discover how this works and could be a huge benefit to society in so many ways. Just imagine a style of architecture which could reduce crime and appeal to everyone solely through the use of materials, proportion and detailing...the astute readers of this blog might have already worked out where I am going with this! For me, classical architecture, like classical music, has this effect and judging by the popularity of cities like Venice, Florence, Rome, Paris and Bath, I'm not the only one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Pal.del Popolo. Photo: Nick Carter&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pal.del Popolo. Photo: Nick Carter&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Piazza del Popolo, Rome. Photo: Nick Carter&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	I don't want to appear narrow minded and I appreciate that my thoughts on this are too biased to be of any use. However, I think many, if not all, architects have been given a bias from their education which needs to be overridden. To neutralise these prejudices, maybe we should judge buildings on whether it is therapeutic or stressful to look at them. It would be an interesting way of looking at architecture. For me therapeutic building include works by Bramante, Palladio, Gibbs, Chambers and Nash. This way of looking at architecture is not new; it was central to the neo-classicist's rejection of baroque during the mid-18th century. For example, Robert Adam's brother James criticises the overcrowded decoration at St Peter's Basilica because, he felt that...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;em&gt;&quot;... the eye is quite fatigued with a long examination of minute parts that seem to be pieces put together by chance... the entablature is broke at every instant and leaves no range, no repose for the eye.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	He also dismisses Borromini and Michelangelo for similar faults. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I've often thought that a good building is one that you like even if you have a headache and my aim is to design architecture which is peaceful to look at or 'easy on the eye' to use a hackneyed phrase. This seems an obvious endeavour but within the profession, architects are praised for being 'challenging' which is quite the opposite. People want Mozart but they are given Stockhausen instead. Great as Stockhausen is, you need to be a music enthusiast to like him, and that's the problem, the frozen music of our cities needs to appeal to as many people as possible and not just the few who are interested in architecture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Specialists in any artistic field can have a have a habit of developing a different taste to the public at large which they snobbishly dismiss as bourgeois and 'too easy'. A film critic is not going to enjoy a slushy romcom crowd pleaser, they will prefer a tedious arthouse film which will be undoubtedly worthy but utterly boring to most 'normal' people. Architects are just the same, they think and dream about buildings day and night which gives them an idiosyncratic taste. And it's a problem because architects with their minority taste get to decide what buildings should look like. To get over this, architects should aim to appeal to a broad range of people instead of just themselves. Perhaps then we would design buildings which, like the music of Mozart, give us a sense of peace and stop our inner dogs from barking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;francis-terry&quot;&gt;Francis Terry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Villa Lante. Photo: Nick Carter&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Villa Lante. Photo: Nick Carter&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Villa Lante. Photo: Nick Carter&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Glad to be Pastiche</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/amy-winehouse.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Amy Winehouse (Kary Stewart @karyignite)&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/thumbs/amy-winehouse.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amy Winehouse (Kary Stewart @karyignite)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo: Kary Stewart @karyignite&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The definition of Pastiche is 'an artistic work in a style that imitates that of another work, artist, or period.'  I imitate historic buildings, rather than inventing new styles, and with this in mind, it may seem fair game to direct the word at my work. It contains the word 'past', making it the perfect insult against Neo-Classical architects. The sound of it has a slightly cloying character, like 'serviette' or 'pulchritude', but having considered the meaning behind any criticism, I have concluded that I'm happy to be labelled this way as I believe the act of copying is an important part of creating anything. Children learn by imitation and so do grown-ups.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pastiche originates from the Italian noun 'pasticcio' which is a pie filler or pâté made from diverse ingredients. This name was adopted in the 18th century for 'pasticcio' operas, which were a composite work or medley using portions of other composers work. Mozart's imitation of the baroque style is seen as a pastiche, and Tchaikovsky's, in turn, imitated Mozart.  This tradition in music continued down to our own time, with Amy Winehouse's pastiches of classic soul and R&amp;amp;B.  In film, Quentin Tarantino's 'Kill Bill' pays homage to Westerns as well as Kung Fu cinema.  Tarantino's attitude of 'steal from everyone' is the cornerstone of the pasticheur's philosophy.  Literary examples abound, as language itself evolves through endless repetition and rearrangements. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The word pastiche can be applied to all artists from Giotto to Picasso. The tradition of painting, like all art forms, builds on the work of previous generations, for example, Manet is a pastiche of Velasquez, Velasquez of Titian, Titian of Bellini and so it goes on. This practice is not confined to traditional painting; the modernists are just the same, as Picasso imitated African art and Gauguin the indigenous art from the Tahiti, while Goya influenced the Chapman Brothers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Art without the influence of previous work is less worthy because it is not part of a long, artistic tradition which society understands. It is not just a matter of stealing. A work of art, within a tradition, automatically develops the language, as it is impossible to copy anything exactly.  This is particularly so in architecture, where client's demands, building regulations and a myriad of other variables all conspire to produce an original work. These alterations further enrich tradition for the architects of the future. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The whole history of classical architecture is based on pastiche as each generation copies from earlier buildings and historic pattern books. I copy the Georgians, the Georgians copied Palladio, Palladio copied the Romans, the Romans copied the Greeks, the Greeks copied the Babylonians and the Babylonians copied the Egyptians. By this analysis, the greatest works of architecture including the Parthenon, and the Pantheon - as well as simpler buildings, like Georgian terraces or Haussmann's Paris, are all pastiche. Unsurprisingly, I am very happy to be a member of this club. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/brighton-pavillion.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/thumbs/brighton-pavillion.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brighton Pavillion&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Avoiding pastiche prevents playfulness of architecture, reducing buildings to bland conformity. Buildings like Brighton Pavilion, which is a medley of Chinese, Indian and Gothic architecture would not be possible if Nash was trying to avoid pastiche. Architecture should tell stories and transport people to another time and place. I sometimes feel that the people who hate pastiche have a joyless puritanical streak, which prevents them from appreciating the architecture to the full.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Judging architectural merit by whether it is pastiche or not is flawed because the ability to know which building came first is essential to knowing which building is original and which is a pastiche. The problem is that most people have no idea of the chronology of architecture and so are unable to discern which is pastiche and which is not. People see buildings and respond to them emotionally with the heart rather than academically with the head.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The fear of being pastiche runs deep with architects and therefore work is judged on how innovative it is rather than its intrinsic merit. I think that architects should not aim at originality but try for the far harder goal of beauty. Beauty in building is so rare, architects need all the help they can get to achieve it.  If imitation helps accomplish this scarce quality, architects should roll up their sleeves, don their aprons and cook up some delicious pasticcios. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
Francis Terry
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/palladian-bridge-at-stowe.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/thumbs/palladian-bridge-at-stowe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Palladian Bridge at Stowe&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;tiny&quot;&gt;Photography by Nick Carter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/glad-to-be-pastiche/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/glad-to-be-pastiche/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
