<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Francis Terry and Associates</title>
    <description>Francis Terry and Associates are designers of new-build and restorations of classical Georgian style architecture and country houses
</description>
    <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ftanda.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:01:18 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:01:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Country House in Northamptonshire</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2020/07/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2020/07/thumbs/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis Terry and Associates are pleased that planning permission has been granted for a new country house in Northamptonshire. This is great news and shows that amongst all the confusion of the past few months things are moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house is based on the manor house tradition, using local iron stone with smooth ashlar architectural elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2020/07/02.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2020/07/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/2020-07-03-news-new-country-house/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/2020-07-03-news-new-country-house/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Can Beautiful Homes Be Built in a Factory?</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/social.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Can Beautiful Homes Be Built in a Factory?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As lockdown is slowly being relaxed, more building sites are looking to return to productivity.  This is obviously problematic – from the restrictions of welfare facilities on sites to many trades trying to work around each other.  Is there a safer, easier to police way of building houses that would enable social distancing to be maintained whilst still being productive and efficient?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the Covid 19 crisis, housing is still a pressing issue and all the major political parties are keen to show how this problem may be solved. The government has set a target of building 300,000 homes a year by the middle of the next decade. Despite recent increases in activity, the volume of houses built is nowhere near this figure and the problem will only get worse. Policy makers are desperately trying to think of a new way to deliver more houses because the traditional methods of building are not delivering the volume required. Many people think that off-site methods are the only way of solving this problem. The perception is that it would be cheaper and quicker because it would avoid many of the problems of a traditional building site. Minimizing time on site has the following advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building sites must deal with unpredictable weather, including rain, wind, frost or even snow which slows and sometimes halts production. Working in a factory, the temperature can be controlled and working inside also eliminates the problem of rain, snow and wind.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building sites are inherently dangerous.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less time on site means less disruption caused by noise, dust and extra local traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With skill shortages being a real problem on building sites, working off-site in a factory would help because the workers would not need to spend time travelling to different places and they could work in comfort. This would help to retain workers in the construction industry.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality control is easier to monitor in a factory rather than on a building site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these factors work together to make the houses cheaper and quicker to build. nHouse claims it can build a house in 20 days in the factory which can then be erected on site in a matter of hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not in a hypothetical realm here, building houses in factories is already done in vast quantities. Predictably Japan and Germany are leading the way, but the U.K. has already started to embrace this new trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Booth writing in the Guardian (31/12/17) observed the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“One of Britain’s major housebuilders is to prefabricate up to a quarter of its homes in a factory, in the latest attempt by the construction industry to tackle the housing shortage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berkeley Homes, which builds 4,000 homes a year, is planning to create a facility in Kent next year where builders will work to produce up to 1,000 houses and apartments annually which will then be craned on to sites.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Another company, nHouse, is setting up a factory in Peterborough with the capacity to build 400 homes a year, complete with light fittings, bathrooms, bookshelves and kitchens. Production is expected to start in January.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other developers, including Legal and General and Urban Splash, have launched prefab home divisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionalists (like me) should not fear this development because prefabrication has been with us since classical times. There is substantial evidence that the Romans had standard column sizes which were used extensively throughout the empire. But a more critical question to ask is, can these prefabricated houses be beautiful? Beautiful boats, cars, bicycles, furniture, clothes, shoes, or whatever you care to mention, can be made in factories, and so why not houses? It can certainly be done in timber, the Americans have been building attractive prefabricated timber houses for years. To do this using heavy materials like brick is more complex but I believe quite possible. I have seen vast brick and stone wall panels for office buildings being made offsite and so I cannot see why this could not be done for housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/02.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Can Beautiful Homes Be Built in a Factory?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to build in volume, houses must be popular and tap into what most people find beautiful. The modernist style can be very beautiful, but it is not for everyone. Modern style buildings generally fall into the ‘marmite’ category, you either love them or you hate them. A popular house needs to be more general in its appeal. For this I would suggest that designing in the traditional style rather than a modern style is the answer. Every estate agent knows that it is far easier to sell a traditional style house than a modern one, Georgian properties being the most popular. This is backed up by the findings of a MORI poll of 2015 which demonstrates that people prefer traditional style houses to modern by a substantial margin. The traditional style houses for this survey were taken from Poundbury and are new build classical Georgian style properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The popularity of the Georgian style should come as no surprise. The Georgians took beauty seriously dedicating whole architectural treatises to the study of proportion and the recording of beautiful mouldings from ancient Greece and Rome. Modernism, by contrast came from a functionalist origin with the belief that beauty would result as a consequence of building well and fulfilling the brief. But as Robert Venturi and others have observed, the Vitruvian triad of commodity, firmness, and delight, (or in layman’s terms; function, structure and beauty) is not an equation. Function plus structure does not always equal beauty, each of the three needs to be considered separately and with equal seriousness. The simple Georgian terrace or house has embodied proportional theories which go back to Palladio and ultimately ancient Greece and Rome. This is why they are generally perceived to be beautiful and the reason why they are so popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Georgian style and specifically classicism is particularly applicable to the current housing crisis because it was built in such a huge volume and at an incredible speed. Classicism was maintained throughout the Victorian era and up until the First World War. The developers of the 18th and 19th century wanted to build quickly and cheaply and so it is useful to see how they produced beautiful buildings within the same parameters. A striking feature of these buildings is the repetition of all architectural elements. This is as much true for Downing Street as a modest Georgian terrace anywhere in the country. The use of repeated elements makes the building process more efficient because it eliminates one-off items which are time consuming and costly to produce. There is a worry that even if beautiful Georgian style buildings could be made in a factory this would not be desirable as they would all be the same and none of the houses would have any individuality. I do not see this as a problem. I have recently designed a housing range for Halsbury Homes and we deliberately made all the houses look similar and I feel that the repetition gives the buildings better group value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/03.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Can Beautiful Homes Be Built in a Factory?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/04.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/thumbs/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Can Beautiful Homes Be Built in a Factory?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where many new housing developments do wrong, at great expense developers make all the houses look different and the result is a very ‘noisy’ visual experience. The use of repetition has a calming effect on the eye because it does not need to process so much information. Georgian buildings are full of standard products made off-site, these include sash windows, doors, staircases, fireplaces, ceiling rosettes, cornicing and skirtings.  This means that reproducing Georgian architecture is well suited to off-site factory production and the Georgian builder would have happily prefabricated whole houses if it was possible at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Classical style which the Georgian and Victorian architects employed so well has been adapted to so many different materials and building methods. I feel sure that if house builders required classical style buildings to be made off-site in sufficient volume this could easily be done. The reason why so much off-site buildings are so hideous is because of the taste of the designers and that is where the problem lies. Many architects like to make their buildings look original and fear being ‘pastiche’. The definition of pastiche is ‘an artistic work in a style that imitates that of another work, artist, or period’. For some reason architects always try to avoid being labelled in this way, but I feel that as with all art forms, the artist (or architect in this case) is part of a tradition stretching back thousands of years that evolves and develops over time. Generations of architects have tried to make beautiful buildings and it is worth benefiting from their knowledge. To avoid being pastiche is, in my opinion, the biggest stumbling block to the production of beautiful houses. It is a far greater obstacle than the engineering problem of producing beautiful houses off-site. If we can get to the moon and split the atom, the technical issues of making beautiful homes in a factory is well within our capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;francis-terry&quot;&gt;Francis Terry&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;houses-by-francis-terry--associates-for-halsbury-homes&quot;&gt;Houses by Francis Terry &amp;amp; Associates for Halsbury Homes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/05.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/thumbs/05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Can Beautiful Homes Be Built in a Factory?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/06.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/thumbs/06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Can Beautiful Homes Be Built in a Factory?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/07.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/thumbs/07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Can Beautiful Homes Be Built in a Factory?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/08.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/beautiful-homes/thumbs/08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Can Beautiful Homes Be Built in a Factory?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;(A version of this essay was first published last year by the Policy Exchange for their Building Beautiful report)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/beautiful-homes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/beautiful-homes/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Amor Fati - A Classical Attitude to Covid-19</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/amor-fati/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/amor-fati/thumbs/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amor Fati - A Classical Attitude to Covid-19&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘You have power over your mind - not outside events. Realise this, and you will find strength’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt; - Emperor Marcus Aurelius&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this pandemic, with people dying by the thousands and the feared possibility of a global recession of elephantine proportions, I could be criticised for nonchalantly blogging about the finer points of classical architecture. So, I felt it is time to write something relevant to this crisis and from the heart. I have decided to write about how I get through hard times, at least in theory, which you might find useful. I am slightly nervous about posting this, in fact I wrote the first version a while ago, posted it for a couple of days and then took it down. It did not seem the right time, but now certainly is. You can rest assured this is a one off, next month I will go back to discussing triglyphs and metopes in the normal way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is at stressful times like now when many people take comfort in religion, which is fine, but religion has never really worked for me. I was bought up as an evangelical Christian with the belief that if you were not a Christian in a limited and very specific way, you would literally burn in the fires of hell for all eternity after you died. Unsurprisingly I could not reconcile that with a loving god and far from giving me comfort it made me scared and unhappy. Over time I freed myself from these unpleasant thoughts and have now adopted Stoicism which for many reasons suits me well. It is a very positive philosophy and like many things that appeal to me, it is classical in origin and was even espoused by the great roman emperor Marcus Aurelius. He was himself a man who incidentally lived through Antonine Plague of 165 to 180 AD, an ancient pandemic that wiped out a third of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/amor-fati/04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;La Peste, Rome by Thomas Blanchet c 1625. On loan to Auckland Castle&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/amor-fati/thumbs/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;La Peste, Rome by Thomas Blanchet c 1625. On loan to Auckland Castle&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;La Peste, Rome by Thomas Blanchet c 1625. On loan to Auckland Castle&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stoicism is also deeply ingrained into the British psyche, it’s the blitz mentality, it’s Nelson giving orders while dying at Trafalgar and now it is the nurses, like my sister Sophie, who risk their lives while cheerfully caring for the sick. This ‘stiff upper lip’ and ‘no nonsense’ way of getting through life appeals to my repressed public school nature particularly at a time when people seem to get offended by anything and everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I take from Stoicism is the desire to love the hand fate has dealt you, whatever it is. I therefore try not to dwell on things I can not change but instead embrace all the things I can effect with enthusiasm, energy and resourcefulness. ‘Great in theory’ you may say and I’d agree, it does not always work, but it’s an aim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This same attitude was shared by the great stoic Epictetus who said&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Don’t seek to have events happen as you wish, but wish them to happen as they do happen, and all will be well with you’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/amor-fati/02.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/amor-fati/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amor Fati - A Classical Attitude to Covid-19&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of self help books and religions focus on happiness; I feel this is a mistake. Happiness needs to be earned and it is never a permanent state. Who, apart from someone either very stupid or those oblivious to the suffering in the world around them could be happy the whole time? In evolutionary terms the complacency of happiness is dangerous, anxiety is far more useful. A while ago I was at a wedding and I heard a sermon that really stuck in my mind. The preacher made an argument which rested on the assumption that animals are happy in their natural state. ‘Has this man ever watched David Attenborough?’ I thought to myself. I am no zoologist, but from my limited knowledge, life for animals in the wild is anything but happy. Think of the zebra on an African plane, they are constantly looking around fearful of a lion appearing from nowhere and ripping them apart, limb from limb, while still alive. This would be an extremely painful death, which brings to mind the worst of medieval torture. This way of dying is a common occurrence for a zebra, and it is probably happening right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The zebra who wakes up in the morning and thinks…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“…..life is wonderful, how lucky we are to live in such a beautiful part of the world, blue sky…..again! Why are you lot looking around all the time, the lions won’t bother us today, don’t be so pessimistic. Relax enjoy yourself….”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zebra do not think like this for the simple reason that all those zebras are dead. They are what is known in lion circles as ‘low lying fruit’. This is why all zebras who live to any age are constantly worried about their imminent death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should not feel any less sorry for the lions, they have to catch these zebras who are impossibly quick and if the lion does not catch any for a while he or she will be too weak to chase them and so die of starvation. What does the zebra and the lion get out of life? Is their life worth living or are we doing them all a favour by bringing them all to the brink of extinction? ….I would argue not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche asking a similar question with this theory of eternal returns. The question he posed was, would you, with all the suffering of your own life, live it all over again exactly the same. The answer must be a resounding loud YES!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the struggle, not happiness, which gives life its vivid and colourful intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘It’s easy for you to say that’&lt;/em&gt; you may feel, and that’s true. I come from a privileged background and so I really know nothing of suffering to any great extent. But don’t take it from me, take it from Seneca who suffered more than most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I judge you unfortunate because you have never lived through misfortune. You have passed through life without an opponent—no one can ever know what you are capable of, not even you.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In situations like this, Stoics will not waste time wishing Covid-19 did not exist or worrying about the consequential recession. Instead they would focus on what they can change, which is to protect themselves and their families, help the vulnerable and use this down time productively. These hard times are an opportunity to reflect and build resistance so hopefully coming out the other side an emotionally stronger and better person who makes the most of this amazingly beautiful, joyous yet terrifying world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;francis-terry&quot;&gt;Francis Terry&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/amor-fati/03.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/amor-fati/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amor Fati - A Classical Attitude to Covid-19&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/amor-fati/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/amor-fati/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lockdown Mural</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2020/04/02.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2020/04/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Francis is interviewed by his son.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As any crafter will know, starting a project is one thing – finishing it is something totally different!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Francis Terry and his family the lockdown has meant a project which was started in February has become a real focus for quality time together, and as well as being admired by many of Francis’s followers via social media, it was picked up by Architectural Digest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.architecturaldigest.com/story/this-english-family-is-painting-its-way-through-the-pandemic&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;who ran this story&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope it inspires you to start (and complete) something creative if you find yourself with more time during this lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/2020-04-27-news-something-creative/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/2020-04-27-news-something-creative/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Francis Terry Podcast</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2020/04/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2020/04/thumbs/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Francis is interviewed by his son.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us have experienced boredom to some extent or other during this lockdown. You may have noticed that Francis Terry has been overcoming this by trying different drawing styles (see the April blog – &lt;a href=&quot;/thoughts/how-to-draw-like-raphael/&quot; alt=&quot;How to Draw Like Raphael&quot;&gt;How to Draw Like Raphael&lt;/a&gt;).  Another new string to his bow has been uploading his first podcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this Francis is interviewed by his son, and the nuggets of wisdom they discuss include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who was the best classical architect?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s important about classical architecture?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why is Gothic architecture so appealing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis hopes to create more podcasts to entertain himself – and hopefully you – over the coming months. Please feel free to use the social media links at the bottom of the website to message us with suggestions for future talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to listen to this please use the button below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/user-365839898/palladio-classical-and-gothic-architecture&quot; class=&quot;button&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Listen Here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/2020-04-09-news-francis-terry-podcast/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/2020-04-09-news-francis-terry-podcast/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Draw like Raphael</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/how-to-draw-like-raphael/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/how-to-draw-like-raphael/thumbs/01F.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;How to Draw like Raphael&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today exactly five hundred years ago Raphael, the great renaissance artist, died. His body was laid to rest in the Pantheon, perhaps the most sacred and important place in Rome. His mistress, Margarita Luti , was barred from attending the funeral and Maria Bibbiena, his fiancé of convenience was later buried beside him. The day of his death was allegedly his birthday and also Good Friday. The symmetry of Raphael dying on the day of his birth would not be lost on the minds of renaissance intellectuals with their love of clean, pure numbers, harmonic ratios and proportions. Good Friday, the day Jesus Christ died would also have significance and was one of the many parallels drawn between the two. Like Jesus, despite his early death and relatively short career, Raphael’s influence over all subsequent generations is hard to underestimate. Rembrandt, Renoir and Picasso all borrowed directly from him, not to mention the whole tradition of western academic painting. Even the PreRaphaelites who formed in opposition to his work, could not help using is name to define themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raphael also represents a fault line, a B.C./A.D. moment in the chapters of art history books. He, along with Michelangelo and Leonard da Vinci, became the heroes of the high renaissance which was perhaps the greatest moment of creativity the western world will ever see. The youthful and charming Raphael found himself at the center of this vortex and his death heralded the end of a golden age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest praise one can give an artist is to say he or she draws like Raphael. It comes in the same package as writing like Shakespeare or ‘bending it like Beckham’. As I can’t write poetry and don’t play football the latter two challenges are not open to me, but drawing like Raphael… how hard can it be? Picasso arrogantly said he drew like Raphael from childhood. But how good were Raphael’s drawings? Perhaps Picasso picked an easy target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video below shows my attempt and I admit it was harder than the spontaneous lines of Raphael suggest. During this time stuck at home you may like to have a go yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;videoWrapper&quot;&gt;
	&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6CeQcsVCFF8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy drawing and stay safe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;francis-terry&quot;&gt;Francis Terry&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/how-to-draw-like-raphael/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/how-to-draw-like-raphael/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Queen Mother Square, Poundbury, Dorset</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/02.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/social.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Duchy of Cornwall began the creation of Poundbury in 1993 following a master plan commissioned by the Prince of Wales from Leon Krier, the influential pioneer of what has become known as New Urbanism but in fact follows traditional patterns. Krier set the size, the number of stories, and the positions of all the buildings, which for twenty years since its foundation have been added successively from designs by numerous classical and traditional architects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quinlan and Francis Terry were commissioned in 2004 to design the main central space of Poundbury, Queen Mother Square. The Prince of Wales has always acknowledged his debt to his grandmother, Queen Elizabeth the Queen Mother, for encouraging him in his youth to share her love of architecture and historic buildings. Quinlan and Francis Terry were in turn honoured to receive this commission because they have long admired the Prince of Wales for his courage in establishing and continually supporting Poundbury, and also because they have known Leon Krier and Andrew Hamilton for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quinlan and Francis Terry were aware that their contribution to the buildings forming Queen Mother Square would be confined to the details of features such as the use and scale of classical orders, windows, doors, cupolas, balconies, roofs and materials, so they would not be able to reconsider the massing and symmetry of the blocks of the buildings already established in Krier’s master plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/thumbs/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their King’s Point House is a large L-shaped building eighteen bays long that forms the west side of Queen Mother Square with a six-story tower at the southwest angle capped by a lead covered cupola and weather vane. Along the ground floor of the whole building is a Doric colonnade in Portland stone in contrast to the yellow brick of the main façade. In the central three bays of both this façade and of the tower, the colonnade with its unfluted Doric columns is replaced by an arcade of three powerful arches with pilasters of horizontally banded rustication in Roachbed Portland stone and internal cross-vaulted plaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Doric order is inspired by that of the Porta Palio at Verona by Michele Sanmicheli of c. 1555 with a busy frieze including bucrania, shields with circular rosettes, and triglyphs. The spacing of the columns along the colonnade at King’s Point House was set by the spacing of the rectangular triglyphs, which are half the diameter of the columns, and of the metopes, which are three quarters of the diameter and must be square to accommodate the circular rosettes. The ground floor of this building is occupied by a Waitrose food store and the upper floors by offices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/09.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/thumbs/09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/10.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/thumbs/10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/11.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/thumbs/11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/13.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/thumbs/13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/08.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/thumbs/08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/12.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/thumbs/12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work is about to start on the construction of the two remaining buildings of Queen Mother Square, which are on the east side, by Quinlan and Francis Terry. Strathmore House is set at an angle to the square and has shops on the ground floor surmounted by three stories for residential use. Its eleven-bay façade in reconstituted stone and render is a richer version of King’s Point House opposite, echoing its rusticated arched ground floor, while its upper two floors are linked by fourteen giant Corinthian pilasters below a pitched roof with an almost continuous band of attic windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the building in Queen Mother Square, this most shows the influence of Francis Terry, for Corinthian is his favourite order and he also believes that classicism works best through the simple repetition of a strong theme. The parade of Corinthian pilasters is capped in the centre by a pediment, which was not a feature of his choice, as it might be considered to weaken that strong theme of which he cites as examples the Altes Museum in Berlin by Schinkel and the Biblioteca Marciana in Venice by Sansovino, which was hailed by Palladio, together with Sansovino’s linked Procuratie Novo, as “the richest and most ornate building that has perhaps been made since the ancients.” The pediment bears appropriately the coat of arms of the Queen Mother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2013, there was a request from the Duchy of Cornwall to make more of the rear elevation of Strathmore House. This was due to Leon Krier’s ever developing master plan, which now made a formal square at the back of the building. The proposed elevation was not designed to be part of a formal setting, so this had to be rethought. The money available for these architectural enhancements would not be of the scale allowed for Queen Mother Square and so the challenge for Quinlan and Francis Terry was to find an economic yet effective solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As has already been noted, trips to the continent are the quarry from which the practice gains inspiration, and this incident was no exception. After returning from their respective holidays, Francis and Martyn Winney showed each other their holiday photographs of towns in the French and Italian Riviera. Coincidentally they both had independently gotten very excited about the potential of trompe l’oeil as a way of decorating a façade. Francis had seen Place Garibaldi and La Chapelle de la Visitation S. Clare, both in Nice, and Martyn had seen the Palazzo Ducale in Genoa. After much discussion they felt that if the technical issues could be sorted out, trompe l’oeil would be a realistic solution to the back of Strathmore House. This is not the first time that the office had done exterior trompe l’oeil. Quinlan Terry at his Nymphaeum at West Green in Hampshire made use of distorted architecture and painted shadows to achieve the affect of a curved wall from a flat surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design would be to continue the giant Corinthian order from the front around the rest of the building in trompe l’oeil. The whole building would now have a strong yellow base colour like Place Garibaldi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the challenges was how to paint a Corinthian capital economically, as the Duchy could not afford teams of trompe l’oeil artists working to their own calendars. Another solution had to be found. Learning from the fashion for stencilling graffiti as propagated by the likes of Banksy, they decided to experiment with stencils. In order to prove to the Duchy that this was not a specialist operation, they commissioned their receptionist, Jo Knights (who had no artistic training), to cut out the stencils and paint them onto a board. This she did with surprising speed and ease, which gave the Duchy the initial reassurance they needed to go ahead with the plan. Further trials were then undertaken with the paint manufacturer Farrow &amp;amp; Ball so that a sample panel could be built on site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/06.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/thumbs/06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining building, known at the moment only as Building IV, occupies the southeast corner of Queen Mother Square and is to be particularly spectacular, for its three main stories will have the Doric, Ionic and Corinthian orders superimposed as at the Colosseum, but first applied to a domestic façade by Leon Battista Alberti at the Palazzo Rucellai, Florence (c. 1460), and taken up by Palladio a century later at the cloister of the Carita Convent in Venice of the 1560s. This is the first time that the office of Quinlan and Francis Terry has put up a building uniting the three orders in this way. Another more local model, though it is only two stories, is the Customs House at King’s Lynn, built in 1683 from designs by Henry Bell and described in the Buildings of England volume Norfolk 2: North-West and South (2002) as “one of the finest late seventeenth-century public buildings in provincial England.” Building IV follows the Customs House in being, unlike the Carita cloister, a freestanding building with one less bay on the two shorter elevations, and also in having the same hipped roof with dormer windows. With the completion of this ambitious pile, Poundbury will definitely become a town and no longer a village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;West of King’s Point House are Inch Arran House and Arch Point House, both providing shops on the ground floor with housing above, the latter with an attractive splayed one-bay corner in stone. This consists of a rusticated, arched ground floor below two upper stories linked by giant Corinthian pilasters supporting a pediment with overhanging eaves. The ground floors have Palladian Doric shop fronts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/04.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/thumbs/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/05.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/09/thumbs/05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South of Queen Mother Square, Quinlan and Francis Terry have built Newborough House with Escalus House joined to it at right angles, and just to the south Woodman Court. Of varied heights and materials, these buildings form two sides of an open square with trees and parking. Further south is the small Oratory. Newborough House is a long, three-story office building with flats above of yellow brick except for the ground floor, which is faced with rusticated plaster, as are the central three pedimented bays on the north and south fronts, which also have arched openings on the ground floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Escalus House is an imposingly tall building of four stories in red brick with shops and offices on the ground and first floors and flats above. On the north front is a five bay Palladian shop front with a Doric triglyph frieze and a portico with Doric columns. The building has a simple Venetian cornice with stone corbels at centres of about three feet that support a plain stone slab and gutter. This derives from a pediment at the Duomo of Santa Maria Assunta at Chioggia in the Venetian Lagoon by Baldassare Longhena of 1624-47, a masterpiece of High Baroque classicism in a superb revival of Palladian models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/urbanism/queen-mother-square-poundbury-dorset/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/urbanism/queen-mother-square-poundbury-dorset/</guid>
        
        
        <category>urbanism</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mount Pleasant: Fortress or Circus?</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/01.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The proposed Mount Pleasant Circus – a Parisian touch in central London&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/social.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The proposed Mount Pleasant Circus – a Parisian touch in central London&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The proposed Mount Pleasant Circus – a Parisian touch in central London&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“This is a great example of how big developments should work – working with local communities to design real neighbourhoods that work for the existing community.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sadiq Khan, Mayor of London&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London, despite slings and arrows, is booming. It has re-discovered its role as a global city at the heart of a mercantile world economy. This was a role partially forgotten for much of the last century and one which it has arguably not played since the twin disasters of World War I and protectionism ended the international capitalism of the nineteenth century. In consequence, after a systemic decline in London’s population of nearly two million between 1939 and the late 1980s, London’s population is now on track to exceed nine million. Cockney or plutocrat, Somali or Scot, newly-arrived or never-left, where will they all live?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One answer would be to expand outwards. Another would be to gently densify in many different places. This is how London has grown in the past. The terraces of Mayfair and Bloomsbury were greenfield developments of four or five storeys ­almost unthinkable today. And the City of London has grown from two storey medieval thatched huts to forty storey towers on the same street pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, growing out or densifying evenly have been made very difficult by the green belt (which prevents outward expansion) and by the comparatively risky British planning system (which prevents gentle densification thanks to its uncertainty which acts as a ‘barrier to entry’ to small landowners or builders).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main route, therefore, that we are taking to providing new homes is by maximising density on a comparatively small number of sites. We build a lot in a few places. Create Streets’ analysis of nineteen large regeneration and redevelopment sites shows that the typical increase in height is around 230 per cent with only one redevelopment having a final maximum height of fewer than 10 storeys. These sites in turn tend to be controlled by major developers – who can afford the high costs and risks of building ‘superdensity.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But is this what people want? In one poll, only 27 per cent of those polled said they would be ‘happy living in a tall building.’ In contrast 56 percent would not be happy. In another poll, the terraced house and mansion-block flats were, by some distance, felt to be the most suitable ways to meet Londoners’ housing needs. Either something is very wrong with the people or something is very wrong with the way we are running, regulating and incentivising our land and development markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Victorian Warehouse, on Farringdon Road.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Victorian Warehouse, on Farringdon Road.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Victorian Warehouse, on Farringdon Road.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mount Pleasant – the site and the history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create Streets’ first project was a site that typifies these tensions. Mount Pleasant is half a mile northwest of the City of London, on the borders of Islington and Camden. It was a unique site of land in central London which had never had streets running through it and which acted as a barrier to movement through the neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially open fields running down to the banks of the River Fleet, Mount Pleasant became a dumping ground for rubbish generated by the expanding city in the late seventeenth century, with a mound of refuse building up over the next 100 years, hence the ironic name. In 1794 the rubbish mound was flattened to build Clerkenwell Gaol. The prison closed in 1877 and since the late nineteenth century the site has served as a major Royal Mail sorting office and open-air car park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Looking up Mount Pleasant with the Royal Mail sorting office on the left.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking up Mount Pleasant with the Royal Mail sorting office on the left.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Looking up Mount Pleasant with the Royal Mail sorting office on the left.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, following on from a joint Camden and Islington Supplementary Planning Document, the Royal Mail made public their plans to develop much of the site. While the principle was widely supported, the proposals themselves proved deeply controversial locally. In the comments left in feedback forms at the 2013 public exhibition there were over eight times as many concerns expressed as there were expressions of support with the proposed scheme. The main concern expressed (on 66 per cent of responses) was the height and density of the proposal. Professionals were not that impressed either. A well-known developer commented, ‘it’s a very bad proposal.’ The journalist Sir Simon Jenkins added; ‘It is a mockery of localism and drains whatever character might have been installed in this potentially charming corner of London… a bland aesthetic of glass towers and rectangles for foreigners to buy-to-leave.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four main things seem to have gone wrong:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A difficult planning framework which encouraged ‘blocks in space’ not streets and squares.&lt;/em&gt; The London and local council planning framework and preferences makes building the type of highly textured street beloved by most Londoners very hard to do. Rules on light and overlooking, a cultural inability on the part of most planners to insist on popular design and the lack of clear design codes all conspire to encourage bland and ‘lumpen’, cheaply-faced, over-sized buildings which feel as if they have been ‘pulled apart’. Rather than building finely-grained streets and squares on new sites we are building ‘blocks in space’ – Duplo not Lego.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The wrong starting point.&lt;/em&gt; An early decision was made to retain a large proportion of the site for operations and car parking and the remainder delivered in phases. This decision came from a pragmatic view on the future operation of the sorting office without the creative input of a development partner or the community. If a developer, with a focus on financial value, and the local community, with their focus on social value, had been involved in that early decision we believe that a better and more valuable scheme could have been the result.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An insufficiently strategic, connected, or London-wide approach to the site.&lt;/em&gt; The masterplan was broken into four portions each designed by separate architects. It is fragmented and inward facing. Many locals described it as a ‘fortress’, rather than one that seizes the opportunity to open routes north-south or east-west improving not just local but London-wide connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A failure to successfully engage with the local community and some consequently important disconnects.&lt;/em&gt; For example, based on a meeting with the local community, architects and landscape experts working in key roles on the scheme appear to have been unaware of the Christopher Hatton Primary School to the southwest of the site. This may have led to the positioning of a 15-storey tower block opposite the school that caused consternation among teachers, parents and children.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The local community asked Create Streets to work with residents and other local stakeholders to design an alternative. Working over three years we did so. First of all, and on a zero budget, we worked up a high-level alternative master plan. Then, when modest funds become available, we worked up the scheme in more detail and submitted the largest ever community right-to-build order for part of the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Designing with residents not at them.&lt;/em&gt; Our co-design approach involved seven public meetings and workshops; the input of thousands of people locally and across London; and received widespread local and national media attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial alternative master plans were worked up in early 2014 with a small number of professionals and local residents who were reflecting conversations they had had with many of their neighbours. Two designs were drafted that reflected earlier suggestions from the community and encapsulated the public response to the Royal Mail scheme. These two options were presented and discussed at a public meeting on 7 May 2014. Comments made during the meeting included: “It’s just great”; “It’s inspirational”; “wow”; “the whole of London could fight for Mount Pleasant Circus”; “it’s great”; “I’m delighted to see the curves”; “it’s very British.” The preferred scheme was then shared much more widely. Between 28 June and 13 July 2014, the Mount Pleasant Association (MPA) questioned 258 residents over several days on the proposal and their preference between it and the Royal Mail Group’s (RMG’s) scheme. Support for the community’s scheme was overwhelming – at 99 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Site Plan of the Mount Pleasant Proposal.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/thumbs/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Site Plan of the Mount Pleasant Proposal.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Site Plan of the Mount Pleasant Proposal. Retail/commercial shown in blue and residential shown in mauve.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we managed to win some funding a wider team of architects, engineers, planning consultants and surveyors then worked up this scheme in more detail, resolved technical and topographical complexities, ran further well-attended workshop weekends and presentations and presented a revised scheme for a Community Right to Build Order for the South Eastern portion of the site in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This more detailed process was able to lead to a scheme that had about 40 more homes than the approved scheme and indeed more development overall whilst fitting in rather better with the surrounding neighbourhood. Sir Simon Jenkins described it as “seriously visionary” and it was praised by consecutive London Mayors. Boris Johnson called it “very beautiful” and Sadiq Khan lauded our approach to community co-design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/05.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Proposed elevation on Mount Pleasant. Creating beauty with space for balconies.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/thumbs/05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proposed elevation on Mount Pleasant. Creating beauty with space for balconies.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Proposed elevation on Mount Pleasant. Creating beauty with space for balconies.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mount Pleasant Circus was the heart of the proposal, giving the new neighbourhood its name and focal point. Responding to intensely strong community feedback, we also proposed a new Mount Pleasant Gardens outside Christopher Hatton Primary School. This featured traffic-calming, landscaping and increasing the size of the existing open space to create a new well-defined triangular pocket park overlooked on all three sides by houses, flats or shops. This was in place of a road and a tower block. The new flats and shops that looked down on Mount Pleasant incorporated the London Plan’s stringent requirement for balconies without ruining the elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also proposed The Upper Walk. In the Royal Mail proposals the roof of their lorry park was a sequestrated ‘meadow’, inaccessible to the public and visible only to the residents occupying the upper storeys of the surrounding flats. Our proposals instead created a series of open and attractive public spaces, taking advantage of the natural change of height by connecting these spaces by new bridges. Finally, our masterplan proposed strong corners that linked to the surrounding neighbourhood and invited entry into Mount Pleasant. We treated the site’s corners (for example with Calthorpe Street and Farringdon Road) very differently to the approved scheme. Neighbourhood support for this master plan was strong and consistent throughout the design process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven key themes seemed to underpin this clear support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A stronger sense of place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It will help to give a sense of community that this whole stranded area badly needs.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It is so refreshing to have this alternative vision for what is a huge site in central London, with intelligent design and a focus on quality housing, rather than the shoddy second-rate package currently on offer from Royal Mail.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Stupendous, here is new architecture which reflects the London urban character in the area and gives us some good green space.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I want my neighbourhood to contain places that are resonant and useful to our community—rather than dumbed-down non-places dreamed up on computer screens and imposed by developers. I want the history and spirit of my area to be revealed and added to—not obliterated and ignored.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A liking for the less ‘fortress-like’ nature of the scheme, especially at the corners&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It…is no longer a fortress. I urge all involved in the future of this site to think of the benefits of these plans and reject the deficits of the RMG’s universally hated plans.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“A vast improvement on the RMG proposals. The open corners around the outside make the area much more inviting and engaging with the wider community.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The radial access of both schemes make the new proposals ‘belong’ to the community.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preferring the positioning of the open space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Islington needs well-designed green space. Your design provides for that. Good luck!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“A logical ‘green’ pathway which will encourage residents and visitors to enjoy the environment rather than just trying to get through or past it. It is a viable opportunity to make real improvements to the area.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preferring the lack of high rise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I fully support the Create Streets alternative scheme.…development that is on a human scale and responds to the traditional London layout of the area with its green squares and terraces.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Buildings no more than 6-8 storeys high would be good.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The height of the buildings is of great importance and should not exceed eight storeys.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A strong liking for Mount Pleasant Circus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It’s important to support ideas like the Circus which continues that sense of civic dignity and social porosity. It adds to London’s historic mix.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I instantly loved the Circus design.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The circus is elegant, enriching the whole area and breaking up a continuous run from one end to the other. This is impressive, well done!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Mount Peasant Circus proposal is inspiring. The cross-roads through a round park will intrigue and entertain users. It is playful.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A preference for the more traditional façade design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The new plan is fit for human beings: it works in every practical way and it has charm and dignity.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The frontages attest to a more nuanced and far less hostile response to the locale, while keeping to density targets.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An appreciation that the proposal has been created with the local community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Thank you so much for supporting the local community.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Profound thanks to all who have given freely of their time and expertise to develop these plans.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/06.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The junction of Mount Pleasant and Warner Street.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/thumbs/06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The junction of Mount Pleasant and Warner Street.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The junction of Mount Pleasant and Warner Street.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our work at Mount Pleasant has had an impact on the national discussion about planning, design and how to work with residents not at them. However, despite coming very close to securing an alternative planning permission and the support of a major investor and mixed-use developer, we did not win this battle. In 2017 Royal Mail sold the site to Taylor Wimpey, who are at present building out the rather mundane initial planning permission which was readily able to secure planning consent but is ill equipped to create a neighbourhood of which London can be proud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team: Create Streets, Francis Terry and Associates, calfordseaden, Maddox Associates, Urban Engineering Studio (David Taylor), Space Syntax, Alexandra Steed Urban.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1) A complete and unedited record of comments can be seen at Boys Smith et al, (2015) &lt;em&gt;Mount Pleasant Circus and Fleet Valley Gardens,&lt;/em&gt; pp. 54-7.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/07.jpg&quot; title=&quot;A watercolour of the proposal as seen from Warner Street.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/01/thumbs/07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A watercolour of the proposal as seen from Warner Street.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A watercolour of the proposal as seen from Warner Street.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/urbanism/mount-pleasant-fortress-or-circus/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/urbanism/mount-pleasant-fortress-or-circus/</guid>
        
        
        <category>urbanism</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>West Hampstead: What is a Mansion Block?</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/social.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When does a mansion block cease to be a mansion block? London’s second ever neighbourhood plan (in Fortune Green and West Hampstead) was very clear that residents valued the neighbourhood’s red brick mansion blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The main architectural feature of the Area is the notable red brick Victorian and Edwardian terraces and mansion blocks. These buildings have numerous design features, detailing and characteristics - which are highly valued and appreciated. The Area therefore has a strong and distinct architectural heritage- including a significant number of listed buildings as well as large conservation areas - which are extremely important in signifying the Area’s look and feel. Preserving and enhancing the architectural heritage of Fortune Green and West Hampstead is of great importance to local residents.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Site of proposal as seen from West End Lane, looking north.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Site of proposal as seen from West End Lane, looking north.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Site of proposal as seen from West End Lane, looking north.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Architectural character of West Hampstead.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Architectural character of West Hampstead.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Architectural character of West Hampstead.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Architectural character of West Hampstead.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Architectural character of West Hampstead.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, many local residents were therefore dismayed when, shortly after their Neighbourhood Plan was agreed, the local council made proposals for a development on their own land which, though not entirely without merit many felt only paid lip service to the local neighbourhood’s preferences. As so often, due to the ‘design disconnect’ which infects nearly all communication between professional designers and the wider public, it was a case of professionals using words to insist that a proposal was in keeping and of residents looking at pictures and responding that it self-evidently was not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working initially for local residents and then for a commercial tenant, Create Streets created an alternative proposal to show how a different approach could both fit in more harmoniously but also provide more space for shops and homes. We called our proposals Rudying Mansions and West End Mews though it also included two further mansion blocks (Railway Mansions and Potteries Mansions) and a pocket park (Potteries Green).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/05.jpg&quot; title=&quot;West End Mews with Rudying, Railway and Potteries Mansions.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;West End Mews with Rudying, Railway and Potteries Mansions.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/06.jpg&quot; title=&quot;West End Mews with Rudying, Railway and Potteries Mansions.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;West End Mews with Rudying, Railway and Potteries Mansions.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/07.jpg&quot; title=&quot;West End Mews with Rudying, Railway and Potteries Mansions.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;West End Mews with Rudying, Railway and Potteries Mansions.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;West End Mews with Rudying, Railway and Potteries Mansions.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began, as we always do, by examining the surrounding streets. West End Lane is the main local high street running to the immediate west of the site. It is visually characterised by largely red brick elevations, visual complexity and decoration, a mixture of flats above shops and mansion blocks with white detailing on the brickwork, bay windows and modest set-backs from pavement. It is predominantly three to five storeys. Lymington Road is the residential road that abuts the north of the site. It is characterised by red bricks, white detailing, generous front gardens, semi-detached houses and what Osbert Lancaster termed ‘Pont-street’ Dutch or ‘Jacobethan’ design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our proposals replaced the existing business and employment space on the site with nearly 17,000 square metres of development. This was composed of 97 homes (including 11 mews houses and 8 maisonettes), 5,000 square metres of flexible employment space (with high floor to ceiling heights and dedicated service access), 550 square metres of shops and over 100 square metres of communal space. The scale was a mixture of two storey mews houses, five storey mansions and one six storey mansion block along West End Lane. The proposed detailing and names of the new Mansion blocks were intended to ‘fit in’ with the area and with the Fortune Green and West Hampstead Neighbourhood Plan. The average residential density was 153 homes per hectare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/08.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The architecture of West Hampstead has a very clear identity.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The architecture of West Hampstead has a very clear identity.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/09.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The architecture of West Hampstead has a very clear identity.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The architecture of West Hampstead has a very clear identity.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/10.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The architecture of West Hampstead has a very clear identity.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The architecture of West Hampstead has a very clear identity.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The architecture of West Hampstead has a very clear identity.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/11.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The architecture of West Hampstead has a very clear identity.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The architecture of West Hampstead has a very clear identity.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The masterplan had six main elements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;West End Mews&lt;/strong&gt; - a conventional London mews with two storey houses running along the north of the site. It was entered via an arch off West End Lane and had a modest paved square at its entrance. A Communal shop (conceived as a flexible community-run not-for-profit coffee bar, community restaurant, meeting room or events space) looked out onto the square. The houses had private gardens backing onto the private gardens of Lymington Road.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potteries Green&lt;/strong&gt; – a neighbourhood pocket park at the end of West End Mews.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rudying Mansions&lt;/strong&gt; – a conventional six storey mansion block (five storeys with sixth set back) running along West End Lane. With ground floor retail and access to two modest communal gardens.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Railway Mansions and Potteries Mansions&lt;/strong&gt; – two conventional five storey mansion blocks between Potteries Path and West End Mews. They were composed of flats above maisonettes. Both mansion blocks had use of modest communal gardens as well as access to Potteries Path and Potteries Green.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ongoing commercial use&lt;/strong&gt; – the development sat upon an area of flexible business space to permit the ongoing functioning of Travis Perkins or of a similar commercial operation. Access to this was from a dedicated ramp at the South East corner of the site underneath Rudying Mansions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The names were intended to reflect the history of the site. In the middle ages the area was known as le Rudyng, a name which indicates a woodland clearing before changing its name to West End.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the mansion blocks had their top storey set back and there would have been potential for green roofs and terraces. All mansion blocks had access to communal gardens for estate residents in addition to access to Potteries Green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mews houses were set along the more sensitive north of the site with private rear gardens between them and the gardens of Lymington Road. All the buildings, West End Mews and Potteries Green are set above the basement commercial space. The typology, detailing, massing and urban form were conceived, in line with the local Neighbourhood Plan, to fit in with the wider neighbourhood and conservation and ‘look as if they have always been there’ with red bricks, white detailing and vertically elevated windows and balconies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three mansion blocks running along the south of the site were deliberately separated to break up the scale and increase light into West End Mews. The reason for adopting such a conventional approach was to ensure that these quite large new buildings fit in as well as possible and did not contradict the conservation area or the local Neighbourhood Plan. Access to the commercial space at below ground level was via a ramp running below Rudying Mansions on the south of the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We provided our plans free to the local council. They proved very popular with local residents and also featured in London’s Evening Standard. Sadly, they did not appeal to local officials and so Rudying Mansions and West End Mews will never be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team: Create Streets, Francis Terry and Associates, calfordseaden.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/12.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Red Brick with ornament and white detailing predominates in West Hampstead.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red Brick with ornament and white detailing predominates in West Hampstead.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Red Brick with ornament and white detailing predominates in West Hampstead.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/13.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Red Brick with ornament and white detailing predominates in West Hampstead.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red Brick with ornament and white detailing predominates in West Hampstead.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/14.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Red Brick with ornament and white detailing predominates in West Hampstead.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red Brick with ornament and white detailing predominates in West Hampstead.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/15.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Red Brick with ornament and white detailing predominates in West Hampstead.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/02/thumbs/15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red Brick with ornament and white detailing predominates in West Hampstead.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/urbanism/west-hampstead-what-is-a-mansion-block/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/urbanism/west-hampstead-what-is-a-mansion-block/</guid>
        
        
        <category>urbanism</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Little Oval: Cricket and Gasworks</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/social.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bird's Eye view of Little Oval proposal&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Bird's Eye view of Little Oval proposal&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“An Odean went past, a cooling tower,
And someone running up to bowl”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Whitsun Weddings, Philip Larkin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gas holders have been a distinctive feature of English cities for over a century. Particularly recognisable have been those overlooking the Oval Cricket Ground in South London with their shape quietly echoing the name and form of Surrey County Cricket Club’s home ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the transfer to natural gas and the creation of the national grid pipework means that London no longer needs gasholders. The site, formerly a dairy belonging to the Duchy of Cornwall, is now being redeveloped by the Berkeley Group. Their masterplan is spatially well conceived and is much better than many central London developments. However, many neighbours consider it too bulky, too high and too anonymous ‘could be anywhere’. In 2015 therefore, at the request of, and working with, the local neighbourhood forum, residents from the Kennington Park Estate and the Save Oval Campaign Group we drew up a sketch alternative master plan. We called it Little Oval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Gas holder and pub.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gas holder and pub.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Gas holder and pub.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Georgian and Victorian Kennington and Oval.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Georgian and Victorian Kennington and Oval.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Georgian and Victorian Kennington and Oval.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Georgian and Victorian Kennington and Oval.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/thumbs/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Georgian and Victorian Kennington and Oval.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/05.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Georgian and Victorian Kennington and Oval.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/thumbs/05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Georgian and Victorian Kennington and Oval.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little Oval delivers identical retail and job-generating commercial space. It can deliver a comparable (though slightly lower) number of homes. Its key features are a green route from Kennington Park to Kennington Lane, a traditional medium rise street pattern, a public circus (‘Gasholder Circus’) taking advantage of the ‘iron’ aesthetic of the Victorian gas works and the other gasholder being used as a green public space (‘Little Oval’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our local survey it was far more popular. 92 per cent of those filling in our online survey preferred it. It received an average rating (out of 10) of 8.13 compared to 2.97 for the conventional scheme. Only eight per cent of local residents supported the high-rise approach being taken in nearby Vauxhall and Nine Elms whose long-term future has been characterised as one of tumbleweed and wind canyons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/06.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Plan for Little Oval, keeping two of the historic gas holder as public spaces.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/thumbs/06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plan for Little Oval, keeping two of the historic gas holder as public spaces.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Plan for Little Oval, keeping two of the historic gas holder as public spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little Oval keeps two, not one, of the iconic gas holders and uses both as public spaces. It is lower rise (three to eight storey) and has a much stronger ‘sense of place’ by developing an exciting and new ‘iron aesthetic’ to respond to the gasholder legacy and which perhaps echoes some of the balconies and ironwork of towns such as New Orleans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbourhoods can change and still remain true to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team: Create Streets, Francis Terry and Associates, John Spence, Urban Engineering Studio (David Taylor).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/07.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Ironwork balconies in New Orleans.&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/urbanism/03/thumbs/07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ironwork balconies in New Orleans.&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ironwork balconies in New Orleans.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/urbanism/little-oval-cricket-and-gasworks/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/urbanism/little-oval-cricket-and-gasworks/</guid>
        
        
        <category>urbanism</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
