<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Francis Terry and Associates</title>
    <description>Francis Terry and Associates are designers of new-build and restorations of classical Georgian style architecture and country houses
</description>
    <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ftanda.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 12:19:41 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 12:19:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why does my Puppy like Mozart?</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/thumbs/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Why does my Puppy like Mozart?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	We recently bought a puppy and discovered that he much prefers classical music to pop. You might think that I have brainwashed our new pet, but we only had him a few days when I discovered this, and most of the music played in our house is instigated by my teenage children whose taste is decidedly unclassical. I am not alone in this discovery; after a short amount of research I found that numerous studies revealed dogs like some types of music and not others. One such piece of research showed that shelter dogs were found to be more relaxed and quieter when they were listening to classical music and barked more when heavy metal was playing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	From this it seems that dogs are born with discernible musical tastes which effects their moods and this seems to be consistent throughout the species. It would be interesting to know whether similar generalisation can be applied to humans. Certainly, artists as great as Bach or Mozart seem to transcend all cultural barriers and studies have shown that their music has a therapeutic effect. Classical music has been successful piped into crime ridden areas to reduce the instances of violence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Various types of music certainly produce particular moods in us - it would be interesting to know which types of architecture affect us in in different ways. Architecture does affect your moods, a brutalist housing development will put you in a different frame of mind to Renaissance church or Rococo boudoir. It would be amazing to discover how this works and could be a huge benefit to society in so many ways. Just imagine a style of architecture which could reduce crime and appeal to everyone solely through the use of materials, proportion and detailing...the astute readers of this blog might have already worked out where I am going with this! For me, classical architecture, like classical music, has this effect and judging by the popularity of cities like Venice, Florence, Rome, Paris and Bath, I'm not the only one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Pal.del Popolo. Photo: Nick Carter&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pal.del Popolo. Photo: Nick Carter&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Piazza del Popolo, Rome. Photo: Nick Carter&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	I don't want to appear narrow minded and I appreciate that my thoughts on this are too biased to be of any use. However, I think many, if not all, architects have been given a bias from their education which needs to be overridden. To neutralise these prejudices, maybe we should judge buildings on whether it is therapeutic or stressful to look at them. It would be an interesting way of looking at architecture. For me therapeutic building include works by Bramante, Palladio, Gibbs, Chambers and Nash. This way of looking at architecture is not new; it was central to the neo-classicist's rejection of baroque during the mid-18th century. For example, Robert Adam's brother James criticises the overcrowded decoration at St Peter's Basilica because, he felt that...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;em&gt;&quot;... the eye is quite fatigued with a long examination of minute parts that seem to be pieces put together by chance... the entablature is broke at every instant and leaves no range, no repose for the eye.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	He also dismisses Borromini and Michelangelo for similar faults. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I've often thought that a good building is one that you like even if you have a headache and my aim is to design architecture which is peaceful to look at or 'easy on the eye' to use a hackneyed phrase. This seems an obvious endeavour but within the profession, architects are praised for being 'challenging' which is quite the opposite. People want Mozart but they are given Stockhausen instead. Great as Stockhausen is, you need to be a music enthusiast to like him, and that's the problem, the frozen music of our cities needs to appeal to as many people as possible and not just the few who are interested in architecture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Specialists in any artistic field can have a have a habit of developing a different taste to the public at large which they snobbishly dismiss as bourgeois and 'too easy'. A film critic is not going to enjoy a slushy romcom crowd pleaser, they will prefer a tedious arthouse film which will be undoubtedly worthy but utterly boring to most 'normal' people. Architects are just the same, they think and dream about buildings day and night which gives them an idiosyncratic taste. And it's a problem because architects with their minority taste get to decide what buildings should look like. To get over this, architects should aim to appeal to a broad range of people instead of just themselves. Perhaps then we would design buildings which, like the music of Mozart, give us a sense of peace and stop our inner dogs from barking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;francis-terry&quot;&gt;Francis Terry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Villa Lante. Photo: Nick Carter&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Villa Lante. Photo: Nick Carter&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Villa Lante. Photo: Nick Carter&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/why-does-my-puppy-like-mozart/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Glad to be Pastiche</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/amy-winehouse.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Amy Winehouse (Kary Stewart @karyignite)&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/thumbs/amy-winehouse.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amy Winehouse (Kary Stewart @karyignite)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo: Kary Stewart @karyignite&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The definition of Pastiche is 'an artistic work in a style that imitates that of another work, artist, or period.'  I imitate historic buildings, rather than inventing new styles, and with this in mind, it may seem fair game to direct the word at my work. It contains the word 'past', making it the perfect insult against Neo-Classical architects. The sound of it has a slightly cloying character, like 'serviette' or 'pulchritude', but having considered the meaning behind any criticism, I have concluded that I'm happy to be labelled this way as I believe the act of copying is an important part of creating anything. Children learn by imitation and so do grown-ups.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pastiche originates from the Italian noun 'pasticcio' which is a pie filler or pâté made from diverse ingredients. This name was adopted in the 18th century for 'pasticcio' operas, which were a composite work or medley using portions of other composers work. Mozart's imitation of the baroque style is seen as a pastiche, and Tchaikovsky's, in turn, imitated Mozart.  This tradition in music continued down to our own time, with Amy Winehouse's pastiches of classic soul and R&amp;amp;B.  In film, Quentin Tarantino's 'Kill Bill' pays homage to Westerns as well as Kung Fu cinema.  Tarantino's attitude of 'steal from everyone' is the cornerstone of the pasticheur's philosophy.  Literary examples abound, as language itself evolves through endless repetition and rearrangements. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The word pastiche can be applied to all artists from Giotto to Picasso. The tradition of painting, like all art forms, builds on the work of previous generations, for example, Manet is a pastiche of Velasquez, Velasquez of Titian, Titian of Bellini and so it goes on. This practice is not confined to traditional painting; the modernists are just the same, as Picasso imitated African art and Gauguin the indigenous art from the Tahiti, while Goya influenced the Chapman Brothers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Art without the influence of previous work is less worthy because it is not part of a long, artistic tradition which society understands. It is not just a matter of stealing. A work of art, within a tradition, automatically develops the language, as it is impossible to copy anything exactly.  This is particularly so in architecture, where client's demands, building regulations and a myriad of other variables all conspire to produce an original work. These alterations further enrich tradition for the architects of the future. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The whole history of classical architecture is based on pastiche as each generation copies from earlier buildings and historic pattern books. I copy the Georgians, the Georgians copied Palladio, Palladio copied the Romans, the Romans copied the Greeks, the Greeks copied the Babylonians and the Babylonians copied the Egyptians. By this analysis, the greatest works of architecture including the Parthenon, and the Pantheon - as well as simpler buildings, like Georgian terraces or Haussmann's Paris, are all pastiche. Unsurprisingly, I am very happy to be a member of this club. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/brighton-pavillion.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/thumbs/brighton-pavillion.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brighton Pavillion&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Avoiding pastiche prevents playfulness of architecture, reducing buildings to bland conformity. Buildings like Brighton Pavilion, which is a medley of Chinese, Indian and Gothic architecture would not be possible if Nash was trying to avoid pastiche. Architecture should tell stories and transport people to another time and place. I sometimes feel that the people who hate pastiche have a joyless puritanical streak, which prevents them from appreciating the architecture to the full.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Judging architectural merit by whether it is pastiche or not is flawed because the ability to know which building came first is essential to knowing which building is original and which is a pastiche. The problem is that most people have no idea of the chronology of architecture and so are unable to discern which is pastiche and which is not. People see buildings and respond to them emotionally with the heart rather than academically with the head.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The fear of being pastiche runs deep with architects and therefore work is judged on how innovative it is rather than its intrinsic merit. I think that architects should not aim at originality but try for the far harder goal of beauty. Beauty in building is so rare, architects need all the help they can get to achieve it.  If imitation helps accomplish this scarce quality, architects should roll up their sleeves, don their aprons and cook up some delicious pasticcios. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
Francis Terry
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/palladian-bridge-at-stowe.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/pastiche/thumbs/palladian-bridge-at-stowe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Palladian Bridge at Stowe&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;tiny&quot;&gt;Photography by Nick Carter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/glad-to-be-pastiche/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/glad-to-be-pastiche/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is Sustainable Architecture With Joey and Francis Terry</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;videoWrapper&quot;&gt;
	&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/j5rwe2DSB-w&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;40% of the world’s carbon is generated by the construction industry. With the Climate Emergency in mind, architects are now considering how to build in a more sustainable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this video Francis Terry discusses with his son Joey what ways architects can address these pressing issues, and how traditional construction methods and materials can contribute to the debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;francis-terry&quot;&gt;Francis Terry&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/what-is-sustainable-architecture/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/what-is-sustainable-architecture/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
        <category>videos</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sustainable Building Materials</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-00.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-00.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sustainable Building Materials&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	I love a good pair of brogues. They last for years and the longer you have them, the better they look. Regular polishing gives the leather the appearance of a freshly fallen conker.  A good pair of brogues will last decades. Trainers, sneakers, gym shoes (I'm not sure of the correct word) do not have this quality. A short run across a ploughed field on a rainy day will ruin a pair of trainers and no amount of polishing will improve the situation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Nylon fabrics, as used in sports clothing, seems to be the 'go-to' fabric for many nowadays and natural materials, like cotton, wool, tweed and corduroy, seem to be less used unless you are a bearded hipster... or a reactionary architect, who peddles nostalgia - like me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-02.jpg&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Prince Charles&quot; class=&quot;half-inset&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	I was heartened to see Prince Charles recently making this exact point during his tour of Australia, where, in an interview with the Australian Financial Review, he said that he was delighted that there is a, “growing awareness of the urgent need to get away from ‘throwaway society’,” when it comes to fashion sustainability.&quot;  His Royal Highness went on to say, “I have always believed in trying to keep as many of my clothes and shoes going for as long as possible (some go back to 1971 and one jacket to 1969) – through patches and repairs – and in this way I tend to be in fashion once every 25 years…”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The Prince of Wales established the ‘Campaign for Wool’ in 2010 which encourages the fashion industry to make greater use of natural fibre.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	This argument can also be applied to traditional building materials. A brick, render or stone building improves with time as the weather will stain the facade and erode the sharp edges. My clients look forward to the day, far in the future, when their new house has softened and mellowed with age. Here are some photos of old buildings which show this beautiful ageing process. Dirt and damage make them more, rather than less, attractive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-03.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sustainable Building Materials&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-07.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Villa Savoye in disrepair&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-08.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Villa Savoye in disrepair&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-04.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sustainable Building Materials&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-05.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sustainable Building Materials&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-06.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sustainable Building Materials&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;quarter&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-09.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sustainable Building Materials&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;quarter&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-10.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sustainable Building Materials&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;quarter&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-11.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sustainable Building Materials&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;quarter&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-12.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sustainable Building Materials&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Many modern buildings do not have this quality, they can look great on the day they are built, but as time goes by, they often look progressively worse, as the concrete cracks to reveal rusting reinforcing bars and plastic seals failing. Many modern buildings rely on a pristine white rendered facade which requires endless painting and repair to look reasonable. This can be seen on these images of the Villa Savoye taken before its restoration. It is interesting to note that the most iconic of all of Le Corbusier’s Villas, depends on constant restoration for its aesthetic appeal.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-13.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Villa Savoye in disrepair&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-14.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Villa Savoye in disrepair&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Similarly, glass facades require regular washing to look new and as environmental concerns become more pressing, one can only speculate about how this massive waste of water and detergents will be perceived by future generations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-15.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Washing a skyscraper&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	The building materials used before the 20th century were brick, clay tiles, stone, slate and timber. All these materials can be recycled and look better with time. Modern construction favours complex constructional systems with a variety of materials. Traditionally a wall was made typically of brick with plaster on the inside and that's it. Today a wall may have a weatherproof skin made of metal or plastic, behind this is a thick layer of petrochemical insulation, then a cavity followed by a steel frame with a concrete panelling system. The joining of these materials will have special systems involving further materials like metal or plastic fixings. This makes the recycling of the wall problematic as the materials are hard, if not impossible to separate. The reason why modern walls are so complex is partly down to insulation, which is there to reduce the energy used to heat buildings. But by solving one environmental issue, another needs to be ignored.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-16.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-16.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A building being demolished&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	One of the great aspects of traditional materials is that they are easy to separate and recycle. Stone and brick, if laid in lime mortar, can be easily taken apart and reused. Likewise, slate and clay tiles on roofs which can be simply removed from their timber batons. Timber can be reused or reformed into plywood or burnt as fuel. If timber is left to rot, it will just go back into the ecosystem with no harm done. Plastic does not degrade in the same way. On a walk in Suffolk, I came across two blocks of polystyrene, which sadly will not biologically degrade. I walked past it a year later and it was still there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-17.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blocks of polystyrene&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-18.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plastic in the ocean&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Increasingly buildings are made from some form of plastic, this could be the windows, doors, insulation, walling and sometimes roofing, in fact, you could probably make a building entirely of plastic, if that was your aim. As plastic starts to fill our oceans, we are all beginning to think of alternatives to petrochemical products. Using hemp or cotton shopping bags is the start of a very real change, but this sort of attitude has yet to permeate architecture. But change is in the air.  As people are starting to see what an environmental disaster plastic is, I hope that architects, of whatever style, will start to look at more natural materials for construction, in the same way that restaurants and food packaging manufacturers often boast of their natural credentials and being free from artificial additives; architects could start doing the same.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-19.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-19.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A bag for life&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/natural-architecture-20.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/natural-architecture/thumbs/natural-architecture-20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vegetables&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	But I do not want to sit in judgement -  traditional materials are expensive and out of the price bracket of many consumers. It's all very well going on about organic food but when you've got a large family and low income, you cannot afford these niceties. As morally dubious as factory farming is, a battery chicken is an effective way of producing food at a low price. These very real moral problems are in most people's minds as they do their weekly shop, but architects are not currently grappling with these issues in any obvious way. Making a building plastic free, for example, is not always possible, but should at least be an aim or intention. As these issues become more dominant, the debates will start informing construction.  Perhaps, in a few years’ time, the great divide in architecture will not be classical versus modern but rather based on the use of natural materials. Architectural style will be seen for what it is which is as a matter of fashion and taste.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
	Francis Terry
&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/natural-architecture/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/natural-architecture/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sketching with my Father</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/sketchingwithmyfather1.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Quinlan and Francis Terry sketching in Ascoli Piceno, Italy, 1983&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/swmf-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quinlan and Francis Terry sketching in Ascoli Piceno, Italy, 1983&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sketching with my father is the corner stone of my architectural education and from about the age of ten my parents took me to see the great master pieces of European architecture.  In each city we visited, my father and I would spend the day sketching while the rest of the family went to the beach. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sketching in a foreign city is not simply a matter of plonking yourself down in front of the local masterpiece, Baedeker in hand.  First you need to find the building or view that is genuinely interesting and this may be a building unknown to the art historians.  My father always took great pleasure in drawing a great work which was never written up.  All too often people are led to appreciate architecture through the eyes of art historians or the celebrity status of the architect.  This my father sometimes took to extremes.  I remember once in Borromini's St Ivo in Rome he took great pleasure in rendering a fairly banal picture frame rather than the church itself. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One also needed to think of orientation, most critically working out where the sun would be in three hours time so that you were not looking directly at it later in the day.  A cafe in the right location was an important element.  Cafes provided the basic infrastructure of a chair, table, water for watercolours and a shield from people watching.  Finding a cafe overlooking the right view with the correct orientation was often fairly tricky.  To satisfy all these criteria was a bit like trying to get a 'Q' on a triple letter score in scrabble.  Our favourite was the Gritti in Venice which for the small fee of a very expensive Cinzano one can sit all day and sketch Santa Maria della Salute overlooking the Grand Canal with no disturbances. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/santa-maria-della-salute-venice.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Santa Maria della Salute, Venice by Quinlan Terry&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/santa-maria-della-salute-venice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Santa Maria della Salute, Venice by Quinlan Terry&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/santa-maria-della-salute-venice-ft-2.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Santa Maria della Salute, Venice by Francis Terry, 1987&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/santa-maria-della-salute-venice-ft-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Santa Maria della Salute, Venice by Francis Terry, 1987&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other major complication was materials.  We had a policy never to carry ink out with us, because of the damage one loosely tightened lid in a suitcase can do to an entire wardrobe.  Far greater than a misplaced red sock in a white wash. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So on arriving in Rome, Prague or wherever, we always needed to find an art shop and buy ink and other materials we had forgotten.  Finding good dip pens was also a problem; once we found a shop in Venice which sold dip pens which had nibs that could be folded away after use which was ideal for travelling.  Ink generally was a bit of a liability sketching even if bought on site.  I remember one particularly windy day in Venice when we were sketching St Stae sitting on the steps by the Grand Canal and a particularly strong gust of wind lifted the bottle of ink off the pavement and caused it to splatter all over my father's rather inferior cream trousers.  This was a source of great humour that evening as we had been urging him to get rid of them all holiday. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We generally brought sketch books with us.  My father until the mid 80s always used canvas bound sketch books bought at Senelier's in Paris.  But since then he has taken up using sketch books with marbled covers which are sold in small boutiques in Venice.  The paper type needs to be chosen with care.  One of my father's marbled sketch books has paper which has the feel of cloth and so bleeds like blotting paper when you try to get a nice ink line.  Other papers do not allow the ink to absorb at all - the problems are endless.  The important issue for my father was that you had a sketch book rather than loose leaves of paper and the sketch book was to be hard backed and not spiral bound.  One of the cardinal sins was to tear a page out because this would ruin the structure of the book. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For several years the whole family went to Venice en masse.  The combination of the architecture with the Lido nearby - proved an unbeatable attraction.  For these trips we used to travel by train which was great fun.  I always loved waking up and seeing some provincial station flash past.  Every year when we passed the suburbs of Verona my father made us crane our necks to see Sanmicheli's Madonna di Campagna. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We usually went to Italy, most often to Venice or Rome, and Florence only once.  My father is not a great fan of Florence because it had too many tourists and not enough baroque to make it worthwhile. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/quinlan-terry-drawing-in-florence-1.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Quinlan Terry drawing in Florence&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/quinlan-terry-drawing-in-florence-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quinlan Terry drawing in Florence&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/quinlan-terry-drawing-in-florence-2.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Quinlan Terry drawing in Florence&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/quinlan-terry-drawing-in-florence-2-b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quinlan Terry drawing in Florence&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On one trip when I was thirteen, we went to the slightly lesser known towns of the Adriatic;- Rimini, Ascoli Piceno, Loreto, Ancona and Split, now part of Croatia.  When sketching one notices things which one would not see otherwise.  For example pilasters in Ascoli Piceno routinely have three rather than five or seven flutes which is an unusual 'specialite de la maison'. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/s-nicholas-prague-ft.jpg&quot; title=&quot;S.Nicholas, Prague by Francis Terry, 1989&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/s-nicholas-prague-ft.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;S.Nicholas, Prague by Francis Terry, 1989&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/s-nicholas-prague.jpg&quot; title=&quot;S.Nicholas, Prague by Quinlan Terry, 1989&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/s-nicholas-prague.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;S.Nicholas, Prague by Quinlan Terry, 1989&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These trips were as much about food as they were about architecture.  On one trip we did a chart of all the restaurants we had been to and judged them on gastronomy, ambience, service and most importantly for a thirteen year old - quantity.  I meticulously filled in a chart at the back of my sketch book each evening.  The most memorable meal we had was the most delicious papardelle in a creamy fungi porcini sauce.  It came to the table in the frying pan served by a waiter who looked like a figure in a Carpaccio painting.  In my imagination I see him with a small red cardinal's cap on but I suspect that is just memory jazzing the scene up a bit, it was over twenty years ago. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We did not always go to Italy, but this was our preferred country by far.  We went to Prague in the summer of 1989 only a few weeks before the Berlin wall came down.  We felt that we were at the centre of Europe and at the centre of history too.  My father was giving lectures to undercover pro-democratic organisations, we also unwittingly smuggled in some xerox parts for some anti-establishment friends of Roger Scruton.  The customs officer found it and was so embarrassed that he did not know what it was that we were let through.  We saw for the first time the fantastic curved forms of Dientzenhofer's and Santini's churches and it was incredibly inspiring.  It made my father feel deprived that we do not live in a time that commissions baroque work as a matter of course. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/francis-terry-sketching-in-india-1993.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Francis Terry sketching in India, 1993&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/francis-terry-sketching-in-india-1993-b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Francis Terry sketching in India, 1993&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The furthest we'd ever been was a trip to India which was paid for by a hotel group who wanted to use my father to design a hotel near Agra.  We were taken all over Rajasthan and deposited at various sites for hours at a time which was ideal for getting stuck in to sketching.  We spent at least two days at Fatehpur Sikri, we also sketched the Taj Mahal, the Red Fort and numerous other buildings. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My father did a measured drawing of Humayan's tomb which has an uncanny similarity to the early plans for St Peter's in Rome.  Whether this is due to a common architectural source or because of the inherent qualities of masonry is a great subject for a PhD, but we never really looked into it.  My father has an aversion to an over academic approach to architecture which I share.  Too much knowledge is definitely bad for creativity, you need to approach it with the naivety and zeal of a child. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/humayuns-tomb-delhi.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Humayun's Tomb, Delhi, India&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/humayuns-tomb-delhi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Humayun's Tomb, Delhi, India&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/red-fort-agra-india-alt.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Red Fort, Agra, India by Francis Terry&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/red-fort-agra-india-alt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red Fort, Agra, India by Francis Terry&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In 1992 we went to Syracuse in Sicily following a classical architecture exhibition in Bologna which was opened by The Prince of Wales.  The Cathedral is a rich blend of three of the greatest periods of Mediterranean architecture.  The main structure is a 5th century BC Greek Doric Temple which has been turned into a church and has some superb Byzantine details - particularly the cosmatesque floor.  To crown it all is a fabulous baroque front built 1728-54.  Our drawings are similar but my father seems to have done far more than me.  I'm not sure why that is, perhaps I wandered off half way through, I know I did spend a lot of time trying unsuccessfully to track down Caravaggio's &quot;Burial of Saint Lucy&quot;.  We had intended to see all the major sites in Sicily but when we arrived in Syracuse and found a west facing cafe we felt that Palermo, Noto, and Agrigento would all have to be visited on other trips. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/il-duomo-siracusa-sicily-qt.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Il Duomo, Siracusa, Sicily by Quinlan Terry, 1992&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/il-duomo-siracusa-sicily-qt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Il Duomo, Siracusa, Sicily by Quinlan Terry, 1992&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/il-duomo-siracusa-sicily-ft.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Il Duomo, Siracusa, Sicily by Francis Terry, 1992&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/il-duomo-siracusa-sicily-ft.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Il Duomo, Siracusa, Sicily by Francis Terry, 1992&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For me this is the point of sketching.  It forces you to go slowly and see things which take time to notice.  So my advice to the students of Notre Dame is to buy a hard backed sketch book with good paper and go to some old and obscure European town.  You could choose the florid baroque of Southern Germany or perhaps the Moorish work of Andalucia and come home with your sketch books filled with work by unknown architects.  Make sure you find time to track down the best restaurants and always remember to buy your ink on arrival. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/san-stae-venice.jpg&quot; title=&quot;San Stae, Venice by Quinlan Terry&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/san-stae-venice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;San Stae, Venice by Quinlan Terry&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/piazza-de-popolo-asoli-piceno.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Piazza de Popolo, Asoli Piceno by Quinlan Terry, 1983&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/sketching-with-my-father/thumbs/piazza-de-popolo-asoli-piceno.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Piazza de Popolo, Asoli Piceno by Quinlan Terry, 1983&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Francis Terry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
(This essay was first published for the catalogue of the Driehaus Prize - 2005)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;div class=&quot;fb-comments&quot; data-href=&quot;http://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/sketching-with-my-father/&quot; data-width=&quot;100%&quot; data-numposts=&quot;12&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;--&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/sketching-with-my-father/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/sketching-with-my-father/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>annecdotes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Proportions in Architecture and Music</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/social.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Architects for millennia have sought to find rules to determine the proportions of every aspect of a building. A window, for example, can look too narrow and thin or conversely it can look squat and fat. How can we work out the right proportions? Is there a ratio of height to width which is perfect? Many architects throughout time have felt there are mathematical formulae to achieve the right proportions. This was a particular interest of Renaissance theorists including the Florentine architect Alberti (1404-72) who saw an equivalence between musical and architectural proportions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I am every day more and more convinced of the truth of Pythagoras’s saying, that nature is sure to act consistently and with constant analogy in all her operations: from whence I conclude, that the same numbers, by means of which the agreement of sound affects our ears with delight, are the very same which please our eyes and our minds.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;- &lt;strong&gt;The Ten Books of Architecture&lt;/strong&gt; by Alberti book IX Chapter V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic maths behind musical harmony has a clarity and simplicity which appealed to the Renaissance mind. If you take two violin strings under the same tension, with one half the length of the other, and then pluck them both, the difference in pitch is an octave which sounds beautiful. In mathematical terms what you are really enjoying is the ratio of 1:2. If the strings are in a relationship of two to three you have a ‘fifth’ and if they are in a relationship of three to four it will be a ‘fourth’, all beautiful sounds as a consequence of being specific and exact mathematical ratios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not just with strings that these ratios can be observed. The same patterns can be seen in different sized bells, different lengths of metal pipe in brass bands or church organ and the different sizes of wood blocks for a xylophone.  The maths throughout these various ways of making different pitches of sound is the same and so they work with each other. If, for example, a trumpet player was to blow down a long brass tube he or she could make the notes of an arpeggio. This wind instrument’s arpeggio would fit exactly into the previously mentioned octave of the stringed instrument, if they are tuned to the same pitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/02a.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/02a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Alberti states, these ideas ultimately go back to the great philosopher and mathematician Pythagorus in the 6th century BC.  He became aware of this when he walked past a blacksmith’s forge and heard the different pitches of the banging on anvils with different sized hammers. When some hammers banged at the same time, they sounded harmonious and others not. He then worked out that the hammers which achieved a pleasant sound were the ones which had a harmonic relationship between each other. For example, if one hammer was exactly twice as heavy as the other, that would produce an octave. He then went on to discover the basic maths of the musical instruments of his day. Through this he came to believe that the same simple number ratios and proportions embodied absolute truth about the harmonic structure of literally everything on earth. But Pythagoras did not stop there, he also was convinced that the same numbers and ratios were consistent throughout the whole universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“If earthly objects such as strings or pieces of metal make sounds when put in motion, so too must the moon, the planets, the sun and even the highest stars. As these heavenly objects are forever in motion, orbiting the Earth, surely they must be forever producing sound.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea, known as the ‘Music of the Spheres’, is the belief that the planets and moon spin on their obits, emitting a hum, which is inaudible to us but if we could hear it, it would be some sort of celestial music expressing the perfect harmony of the universe. The planets which are further away were thought to make a lower hum than the ones closer to earth, it was as if the universe was one massive lute or harp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/03.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/04.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/thumbs/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How wonderful it would be to believe that certain proportions embody timeless irrefutable truths which are consistent throughout nature, music and architecture. It is so satisfyingly neat… but is it true?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, we still look for magical formulae to explain the complexities of the universe and this is as true for Pythagorus as it is for Einstein.  In music the octave, the fourth and the fifth still sound beautiful and are used by musicians both ancient and modern. But for architecture, does the analogy work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I do not think that musical and architectural proportions work the same way. For architectural proportions to be ‘harmonic’ they do not have to be exact. For example, if the double cube room at Wilton was not quite a double cube, is would not be any better or worse, it aims to be a cube and near enough is fine. Architectural proportion is like Goldilocks’s porridge, slightly too hot or cold is fine it is a matter of degree, the closer the better. Music is not like this, slightly wrong is the most discordant sound possible. If an octave is slightly off it sounds completely wrong, even the most tone-deaf person can hear when a violin is even slightly out of tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/05.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/thumbs/05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/06.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/thumbs/06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure Palladio would have enjoyed someone post rationalising one for his buildings in terms of musical ratios, but I do not think he would have been at all familiar with these ideas and he certainly did not use them in practice. I can find no written reference to this Pythagorean musical analogy in his Quattro Libri. There may be some number ratios within his designs which appear to have a reference to these ideas but as D. Howard and M. Longair state in their essay ‘Harmonic Proportions and Palladio’s Quattro Libri’ ‘…this is more likely to be down to the practical advantages of using simple easily divisible numbers’. Which makes perfect sense particularly at a time when buildings were set out by lengths of rope and crudely pegged out on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/07a.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/thumbs/07a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/08.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/thumbs/08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This certainly chimes with my understanding of Palladio’s architectural details. With his orders in the Quattro Libri, there is no attempt to use simple numbers let alone clean musical ratios. For example, the height of his Corinthian order is nine and a half times the length of the bottom diameter (rather that an even ten) and the entablature height is one diameter plus nine tenths (rather than an even two). The smaller scale details of the Corinthian order are just the same, virtually every dimension has a fraction attached and this is true for all his orders. Palladio’s drive was to represent a particular form or shape based on his knowledge of the ruins from Ancient Rome and his instinct for proportion. He therefore used whatever numbers and fractions worked to give him the exact dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/09.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/thumbs/09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is one set of proportions which I believe are inherently beautiful, these are the classical orders from Ancient Rome. Quite why these proportions are so beautiful is hard to fathom but what is clear is they have nothing to do with musical ratios. In John Summerson’s excellent essay ‘Antitheses of the Quattrocento’ he sums it up in the following way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“If you are unwilling to accept the five orders as a gift of a myth, delightful and glorious fundamentally because they derive from an old, forgotten world, then you must argue yourself into believing that, somehow or other, they embody absolute values of proportion and ornament; and that argument is difficult in the extreme.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If proportion cannot be attached to some absolute values all we are left with is personal judgement. There is a story about Michelangelo being criticised for making the cornice on Palazzo Farnese too large according to classical rules. To which he replied, ‘My eye is my measure’. Michelangelo, perhaps justifiable felt that his innate sense of proportion was enough with no recourse to anything else. He was effectively saying ‘I know what I like’, which does not sound like a valid architectural theory but perhaps that is all there is, and we should be honest about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/10.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/thumbs/10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/11.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/thumbs/11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proportions in Architecture and Music&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the office we spend hours analysing our designs and trying different proportions of windows and doors in slightly different places to ensure that we have designed the best possible building within the given constraints. It is worth taking time to get these things right because a well-proportioned building costs the same as a badly proportioned one yet is worth so much more. We do this primarily by intuition. This process is not academic or theoretical, but if some latter-day Alberti comes along and finds musical ratios in my work which ties into some greater cosmic order, I certainly will not complain but it does not make it true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;francis-terry&quot;&gt;Francis Terry&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/962904274&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/user-365839898&quot; title=&quot;Francis Terry&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Francis Terry&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/user-365839898/proportion-and-inspiration-in&quot; title=&quot;Proportion and Inspiration in Music and Architecture&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Proportion and Inspiration in Music and Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/proportions-in-architecture-and-music/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What Is More Important, Materials or Form?</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/rotonda-01.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Villa Rotonda&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/thumbs/rotonda-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Villa Rotonda&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
	Would the Villa Rotonda look good made of cheese?
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	When faced with a client whose budget demands cheap materials, I am comforted by the thought that Palladio had to deal with these exact challenges. All his villas in the Veneto are made from render which is a cheaper alternative to stone, but it looks similar from a distance, which makes me think that even if the Villa Rotonda was made of cheese, it would still look splendid from afar - sitting majestically on a hill outside Vicenza. Sometimes this can be forgotten by an architect as your dream stone house, becomes ‘reconstructed stone’ (which is little more than well-marketed precast concrete) or your beautifully detailed hardwood sash windows become PVC double glazed units. These are client choices and part of the architect’s art is to choose wisely when faced with such compromises.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Some architects argue that the use of good materials and sound construction is what makes good architecture. Some of my classical friends are very insistent that their work is always constructed from load-bearing masonry and constructed from good quality materials. But what do you do when the budget does not allow for such luxuries?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/rotonda-02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Laugier’s primitive hut&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/thumbs/rotonda-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Laugier’s primitive hut&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/rotonda-03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Turin, 2017&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/thumbs/rotonda-03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Turin, 2017&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	The idea that good architecture is essential to good construction has a long history, going back to Vitruvius, but it returned with vigour in the mid 18th century when the Neo-Classicists reacted against the extravagant excesses of the baroque. Laugier drew a parallel between Rousseau’s ideas of the prehistoric human, or ‘the noble savage’, living his/her life in uncorrupted Arcadian bliss with buildings which were free from extraneous and unnecessary ornament. A column in the garden of Eden would carry the weight of a roof and not be merely a decorative ornament. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/rotonda-04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The detailed facade of an old cathedral&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/thumbs/rotonda-04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The detailed facade of an old cathedral&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Ruskin and Pugin further developed this argument into the idea that different materials and construction should affect the form of the resulting building. The concept of ‘truth to materials’ was invented. In typical Victorian style, they saw buildings as morally good or bad, based on these notions. Gothic was good, ‘true’ and Christian while Classical was bad, ‘false ‘and pagan. Gothic is a style generated out of the physical performance of materials while classical is a style that comes from an idea of how a building should look and the material is to some extent irrelevant. Ruskin and Pugin’s ideas were essential to the modernist movement and the fetishizing of structure and materials can most obviously be seen in some of London’s most ugly buildings.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/rotonda-06.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Ugly buildings&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/thumbs/rotonda-06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ugly buildings&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/rotonda-07.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Ugly buildings&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/thumbs/rotonda-07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ugly buildings&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	This way of judging buildings is so ingrained in architectural thought that it hardly needs to be said and it is very much with us now. Architects routinely talk about ‘structural integrity’ or buildings being ‘honest’ or ‘true’ in a way which probably makes no sense to people outside the profession.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Ruskin and Pugin were right about Classicism, it does not let the materials and construction affect how the building looks. Classicism is about form and proportion in the service of beauty.  If you look at the history of the style, classicism uses the same form on a variety of materials. The Triglyph is a classic example, its origin is thought to have come from timber construction with the triglyph as the beam end and the guttae as pegs to hold it in place. This was later copied in stone and used by the ancient Greeks for their Doric temples and all other Doric orders ever since. This form has nothing to do with stone construction, the form itself creates beautiful shadows which work for any material. American classical architects routinely made their cornices out of zinc or copper instead of stone, is a further development of the same idea.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/rotonda-09.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Espino Family Parthenon&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/thumbs/rotonda-09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Espino Family Parthenon&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/rotonda-10.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Tony Hisgett Zinc cornice&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/thumbs/rotonda-10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tony Hisgett Zinc cornice&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	My friend Ruaidhri Tulloch worked on a housing development in Versailles.  Unlike the palace, this project had serious cost constraints. In order to fit with the architecture of the town, they followed the generic local style, but they could not afford to use the correct traditional materials. So they built a traditional urban block out of polystyrene with a specialist finish to look like a lime render. Obviously, polystyrene is a dreadful material on so many levels and lime render would have been so much nicer but given that this was not possible, I feel they made the right decision to keep the form as it was, rather than design in a new style to respond to the technical properties of polystyrene. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/rotonda-12.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Versailles project by 2BDM&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/thumbs/rotonda-12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Versailles project by 2BDM&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/rotonda-13.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Versailles project by 2BDM&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/rotonda-in-cheese/thumbs/rotonda-13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Versailles project by 2BDM&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Trying to create beautiful buildings by simply using construction is like writing a novel and hoping that the correct spelling and grammar are enough to make a good read. But more importantly, the author needs to have something to say, otherwise, their use of language is somewhat pointless. Likewise, an architect must have an intention about how their buildings should look and this cannot be generated simply from how they are made. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
	Francis Terry
&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/rotonda-in-cheese/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/rotonda-in-cheese/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pretty Buildings</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/physics-envy/view-of-the-old-grammar-school-dedham.jpg&quot; title=&quot;View of The Old Grammar School, Dedham&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/physics-envy/view-of-the-old-grammar-school-dedham.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View of The Old Grammar School, Dedham&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Architects are always presumed to be good at maths and physics. This suggests that people feel the primary role of an architect is to make a building stand up, which is curious because architects in the UK are not licenced to carry out this task.  Perhaps architects are to blame as they do very little to dispel this myth.  I suspect that this is because they like to feel they are as clever as scientists.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The fact is that an architect's main role is to make buildings look 'pretty', but that does not sound important enough to justify seven years of education.  This public misunderstanding has, to a certain degree, come from the word 'architect' which is an important sounding word protected by parliament. The word has come to mean the ultimate controller as in 'IT architect' or god as 'the architect of the universe'. This has taken architecture away from its true calling which is an art form to rival music, painting and sculpture.
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Synonyms of the word 'musical' include harmonious, melodic, pleasing and sweet sounding.  Similarly, synonyms of the word artistic include graceful, elegant, poetic, sensitive, elegant and fine. In contrast, the word 'architecture', when applied to things other than buildings, focus on structure and rhythm rather than beauty.  For example, the most 'architectural' plant is something like a cactus - hardly an object of beauty.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When journalists praise new buildings, they often use words like 'cutting edge' and 'innovative', which are more appropriate for science rather than an art form.  This has led to a situation where the word 'brutalist' is a compliment, which is crazy, how can being 'brutal' be in any way praiseworthy?  I would like to see words like 'charming', 'delightful' and dare I say it 'pretty' be applied to architecture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
Francis Terry
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/physics-envy/high-street-dedham.jpg&quot; title=&quot;High Street, Dedham&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/physics-envy/thumbs/high-street-dedham.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;High Street, Dedham&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/physics-envy/shermans-hall-dedham-nick-carter.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Sherman's Hall Dedham&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/physics-envy/thumbs/shermans-hall-dedham-nick-carter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sherman's Hall Dedham&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;tiny&quot;&gt;Photography by Nick Carter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/physics-envy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/physics-envy/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Where does your Chicken Cross the Road?</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/chicken/mika.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Where does your chicken cross the road?&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/chicken/mika.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Where does your chicken cross the road?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	“Why did the chicken cross the road?” is not a great joke.  What interests me more is where the chicken crosses the road in people’s minds.   When asked the question, what do you imagine? I would be most interested in your answer, which you can leave in the comments section below. I have had a variety of answers to this question. Most people, after some confusion, will look upward and slightly sideward as they search their memory, eventually offering an idiosyncratic response such as ‘I don’t really know but it’s going up a hill’ or ‘It’s a road through burnt stubble fields’. The responses are endless and always unique, which has allowed me to delve into the deep recesses of people’s minds via this simple (and rather poor) joke.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	As an architect, I am conscious of the many types of people needed to make a building - each with varying skills and ways of thinking. Architects, quantity surveyors, stonemasons, planning consultants, steel work fabricators, engineers, carpenters, project managers or whomever you care to name all think in their own individual and profound way. All are essential to the success of the project and I have become fascinated by what goes on in someone’s head when faced with the same piece of data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	For me, it is on Dedham High Street, outside my first school. The chicken crosses from the south side to the north and I view it from about thirty feet to the west. The hen is chestnut coloured, which is the standard choice - nothing unusual about that. Here is a photograph of the exact spot.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/chicken/dedham-high-street.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Dedham High Street&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;full&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/chicken/thumbs/dedham-high-street.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dedham High Street&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Both my father and my sister Anna see the chicken crossing the same street as me but slightly further east. Two of my children visualise this event in very specific places around Colchester, where we lived at the time they originally heard the joke. The third, my middle child, sees it in the film Toy Story, where a chicken or something similar crosses a dangerous road. My wife, who is very analytical, does not visualise it at all. If pushed she sees a blank piece of paper with a line representing the road and the chicken is simply indicated by the word ‘chicken’ which I can see written in her hurriedly penned capitals.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Having asked this question to people over many years I have concluded that there are four ways to imagine this event. Firstly, there’s my way (group 1) – in a highly detailed and specific place; secondly are the people who imagine a generic place like ‘in a country road but I don’t know where’ (group 2); thirdly people imagine it as a cartoon or book illustration (group 3) and fourthly there are some people, like my wife, who don’t imagine it at all; to them it is a concept like a mathematical equation (group 4). I asked a member of group 4 why they don’t imagine it and the reply was, “The question is not where did the chicken cross the road, but why”. Such is the logical brain.  I think ‘why’ is usually tied up with ‘where’, - for example, my associate Les (of group 2) imagines this event happening on a busy street in a town. His chicken is a brave fowl, courageously crossing, causing cars to screech to a halt. Reasons for crossing a quiet country road will be different and far less compelling than crossing a dangerous road in a town.  He also tells me that his chicken would cross in a different setting each time he hears the joke. This is quite literally unthinkable to me; my chicken has always crossed in the same place and I could not change it, even if I tried. The different settings for the event, affects the personalities in the story. For example, Les’ chicken is brave to the point of being foolish.  Mine is loyal, crossing the same road in the same place - as she has for millennia, never ageing, never complaining.  She will continue to cross that same piece of the road long after I am dead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Those belonging to group 1 have the advantage of imagining things very vividly, but it is problematic when reading novels. For example, if I read ‘she walked into the dining room from where she could see the fishing boats going out to sea.’ I would start that sentence with our heroine walking into my parent’s dining room, but then I would be sent into a crisis, as the view must be changed from a Suffolk garden to a view of the sea. I will then be faced with a choice of A) changing my location to a dining room with a view of the sea or B) trying to change a very familiar view of a garden into a view of the sea. Attempting option A), I need to think of the only dining room I know with a sea view. This is a house I stayed at in Cornwall many years ago belonging to my then girlfriend’s parents.  I only went there once and we spent as little time in the dining room as possible because the pub down the road was so much more alluring. Therefore, my memory of a dining room with a view over the sea is virtually non-existent. Thinking about it, I am not even certain this dining room looked over the sea. Option B) is even harder. I will need to cut and paste the sea of a familiar view that I have known for years. This does not really work because when I lose focus, the Suffolk lawn and Wellingtonia return. Each option demands Zen levels of concentration and as a result, I do not read novels very often - it’s just too painful.  I am keener on non-fiction, particularly biographies, which involve real places that I can look up. I often think that I would like to be group 2 as they can conjure up images from nothing, but I suspect they do not see these images with the clarity that I do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/chicken/dining-room-1.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The view from the dining room&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/chicken/thumbs/dining-room-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The view from the dining room&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/chicken/dining-room-2.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The view from the dining room&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/chicken/dining-room-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The view from the dining room&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	What this study has made me realise is that we all think in completely different ways. No way of thinking is better than any other way; they just give the thinker individual abilities and experience of reality. Each has advantages and disadvantages. A vivid imagination (group 1) makes you a slower thinker as the brain tries to constantly upload huge files of data and at the other end of the spectrum, the conceptual thinker (group 4) will be able to solve problems at lightning pace, free from unnecessary visual baggage but they may struggle to visualise things with any degree of clarity. In everyday life, we must flip from one form of thinking to another, and I suspect a well-rounded person can do this easily.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 
	This investigation has made me realise that words are a clumsy representation of our internal cinema. I am reminded of a quote from my only famous relative, Joseph Conrad.  In Heart of Darkness, Marlow, the narrator, breaks his story of travelling up the River Congo to make a profound observation on story telling:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	“No, it is impossible; it is impossible to convey the life-sensation of any given epoch of one’s existence - that which makes its truth, its meaning - its subtle and penetrating essence. It is impossible. We live, as we dream - alone.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Heart of Darkness is one of the few novels I have actually read, but I imagined it on the River Stour, which flows past the end of my parent’s garden separating Essex from Suffolk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I’ve never been to the Congo.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
	Francis Terry
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/chicken/stour.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The River Stour&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;full&quot; src=&quot;/images/essays/chicken/thumbs/stour.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The River Stour&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/chicken/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/chicken/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>annecdotes</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Should Architects Just Do as They Are Told?</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/should-architects-just-do-as-they-are-told/01.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/should-architects-just-do-as-they-are-told/social.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Should Architects Just Do as They Are Told?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	A friend of mine runs an excellent restaurant locally and he caused quite a stir when, as a young chef, he refused to give customers mustard if, in his opinion, it did not complement the dish. Some saw this as being wilfully obstructive, others the inevitable consequence of someone who cares passionately about food. This made me think, how much should I, as an architect, push my opinions? Should I simply take instructions from clients and blindly obey, or should I insist on buildings being a particular way?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Architects are known for insisting on things which the client does not want. I’ve heard people say things like, ‘my architect wouldn't let me do that’ and certainly the more eminent the architect, the more of a prima donna they can be. Sir Edwin Lutyens, despite his ‘bon ami’ spirit was abundantly aware of his own importance. There is an amusing story about the building of Heathcote, his first classical house completed in 1908. On a site-visit, Lutyens and John Thomas Hemingway (the client) viewed the space intended for the black marble staircase.  Hemingway said, “I don’t want a black marble staircase. I want an oak staircase”, to which Lutyens replied, “What a pity.”  On a later visit, when Hemingway was shown the completed black marble staircase, he complained, “I told you I didn’t want a black marble staircase.”  “I know,” the architect replied, “and I said, ‘What a pity’, didn’t I?”
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/should-architects-just-do-as-they-are-told/02.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/should-architects-just-do-as-they-are-told/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Should Architects Just Do as They Are Told?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Lutyens evidently felt that the house required a black marble staircase for its artistic integrity and if that was not to the client’s taste that was ‘a pity’ but he was not going to let the subjective preferences of the customer get in the way of his architectural vision. Happy days indeed... for architects perhaps, but not so much for the clients. Though I admire Lutyens greatly, I would never behave like this, partly out of a fear of being sued, but more importantly because I believe that ultimately the house and its choices belong to the client, not the architect. Clients have their reasons for liking things based on their memories and tastes which cannot always be explained but these preferences are real and should be respected. Also, the architect will leave after the house is complete and rarely, if ever, return, but the client must live with these choices on a daily basis. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Lutyens’s hallowed status came out of an attitude to artists which developed during the Renaissance. Before then artists were viewed simply as the craftsmen and their opinions were irrelevant. Michelangelo, the greatest architect and artist of the Renaissance, was seen by his contemporaries as literally divine, sent by God and in effect a messiah of art. Despite our modern day egalitarian pretentious, and the wholesale rejection of so much of the Renaissance spirit, the idea of the hero artist has survived intact. Frank Gehry for example, recently said, “I don’t know why people hire architects and then tell them what to do.” In other words, the client should just trust the architect to do the right thing because they are divinely inspired. This might work for Gehry’s standalone modernist art galleries which could be seen as inhabited sculpture rather than everyday architecture. For the world of domestic architecture, in which I work, the complex and personal requirements of a client need to be considered in great detail, Gehry’s ‘don’t question the architect’ approach would be a disaster.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	In my experience, clients come to architects with a great deal of knowledge and they like to question everything, which I find an enjoyable and stimulating process. Clients often have Pinterest images and photos from magazines or the internet and they have done their research. The decisions come out of a discussion between the client and architect relating as equals, rather than an architect telling their client what to do. Projects are therefore more of a collaboration - which I see as a good thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/essays/should-architects-just-do-as-they-are-told/03.jpg&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/essays/should-architects-just-do-as-they-are-told/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Should Architects Just Do as They Are Told?&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	But within this collaboration my preferences are important to the client and I would not be doing my job if I did not speak up. If the client makes a decision which I think is wrong, after respectfully arguing my point, I will support them in their wrong decision because perhaps it is right for them. Giving advice is not always easy and you need to be careful not to appear dismissive or patronising. I had an experience of this from the client side when I had my first suit made many years ago. I went to Welsh and Jefferies, my father’s tailor on Saville Row. When discussing with the tailor what sort of suit I wanted, the tailor gave me options like, do I want three buttons on my jacket or how wide do I want the lapels, or do I want turn-ups. I would, from time to time, proffer an opinion based on what was in vogue at the time. The tailor would respectfully listen and then politely explain, that though he could do as I required, what I really wanted was a passing fad and in the fullness of time the conventional width of a lapel and number of buttons was the best decision. He was a little condescending but forgivable and I was conscious that I had come to a tailor whose work I respected, and I did not want my influence to force the tailor to make a suit which was not to his taste. This led me to ask whether he had ever made a suit he did not like. Did he ever have clients with greater confidence and strong will who insisted on their choices, not his? He said he had. Karl Lagerfeld, or someone like him, had come in requiring orange suits of a vaguely military design which were not his taste, but he made them as well as he could none the less. I am sure he did an excellent job and the client was very happy with the result.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So back to the original question, would I offer the architectural equivalent of mustard even if did not suit the dish? I think I would, but if they ask for tomato ketchup, I will politely tell them they have come to the wrong restaurant.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
	Francis Terry
&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/should-architects-just-do-as-they-are-told/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/should-architects-just-do-as-they-are-told/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>theory</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
