<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Francis Terry and Associates</title>
    <description>Francis Terry and Associates are designers of new-build and restorations of classical Georgian style architecture and country houses
</description>
    <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ftanda.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 08:43:41 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 08:43:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Orangery in Norfolk</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/124.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Orangery in Norfolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/thumbs/124.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Orangery in Norfolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new orangery at a house in Norfolk, completed in 2017, was conceived as a sensitive yet striking extension to the existing home. Designed to meet the evolving needs of contemporary family living, the space was intended primarily to house a large open-plan kitchen and informal living area—functions that now form the social heart of the modern home. The goal was not only to increase the footprint of the property but also to enhance the quality of light, flow, and connection to the surrounding garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/005jpg&quot; title=&quot;Orangery in Norfolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/thumbs/005.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Orangery in Norfolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architecturally, the orangery takes its inspiration from the Queen Anne period, a time known for its refined detailing and elegance. This influence is most clearly expressed through the inclusion of tall, generously proportioned windows which allow natural light to flood the interior throughout the day, creating a bright and welcoming atmosphere. The use of red brickwork further ties the new addition to the traditional vernacular of the region, reinforcing a sense of continuity between old and new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/012.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Orangery in Norfolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/thumbs/012.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Orangery in Norfolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to achieve a high level of craftsmanship and a subtle, timeless aesthetic, special attention was paid to the construction techniques and materials. One notable detail is the use of thinner mortar joints than those typically found in modern brick buildings. This decision was made to replicate the finer, more delicate appearance associated with historic brickwork, helping the new structure to sit harmoniously alongside both the existing house and the wider architectural heritage of the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/035.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Orangery in Norfolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/thumbs/035.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Orangery in Norfolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Careful consideration was given to proportions, detailing, and material transitions to ensure that the orangery reads as a distinct architectural element in its own right, while still harmonising with the character and form of the original house. Rather than attempting to replicate the existing structure, the design takes a complementary approach—respecting the historic fabric of the home while clearly expressing its own identity. The result is an elegant, functional, and light-filled space that enhances the daily life of its occupants and pays quiet homage to the architectural traditions that inspired it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/097.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Orangery in Norfolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/thumbs/097.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Orangery in Norfolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/orangery-in-norfolk/</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>featured-projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>House in Wiltshire</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/01.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/thumbs/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the joy of so many English country houses is the layered stories in which they are steeped: the distinctive and attractive form that comes from additions and contractions across centuries, and the underlying sense of how they are shaped by the lives led within them. Since the Regency, architects have designed houses that echo this narrative form, which imply history and reflect the aesthetic of these older houses. Edwin Lutyens was a master of such compositions, designing new houses that on one level feel like sketches of old organic houses, but with all the advantages of better building systems. This new house in Wiltshire, completed in 2018, is a contemporary demonstration of this same theme, resulting in a finely modelled house, a two-story, five-bay classical block with low two-storey wings, mansard roofs and an additional eastern range that faces a walled garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house was designed by Francis Terry, one of the leading younger classical architects in practice today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Terry, “the truth is we designed this house from the inside out: thinking about how life would be lived and the rooms that were needed, and then developed the best classical form for the exterior: life came first.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terry is well known for his draughtsmanship and for his skill in drawing out sketch elevations and plans by hand as they are discussed with clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the first part of the project to be realised was the summer house – part pool house, part retreat from the main house – which provided the arena for family recreation. It is a simple classical pavilion, with a portico with a shaped gable as a pediment – with reference to the work of Oliver Messel, the gifted theatre designer who turned to architectural projects in the 1960s and ‘70s, especially in Barbados and Mustique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/thumbs/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the summer house there is a generously scaled large family living room, with changing rooms and a place for al fresco meals in front. It is set in a new walled garden, of traditional vernacular built in brick and flint, and planted with borders on which the garden designer Rupert Golby advised. Golby is skilled in the subtle reinterpretation of the romantic classic English garden tradition with simpler planting and a sense of connection with the wider setting. The summer house project provided something of a trial run for the main house, and much pleasure was achieved in the realisation of the union of architecture, garden and landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/05.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/06.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main house is also satisfyingly simple, and despite its plain, crisp ashlar walls, and the formal rhythm of its sash windows and pedimented dormers, it has a sculpted, slightly baroque feel in the way the shadow is cast between the connected blocks of the composition. There is a dignified, alert quality to the property, which owes much to the rigorous proportions of the house, windows and wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house is faced in a light, creamy Bath stone ashlar, under a slate roof, and set against a wooded backdrop: the south front looks out over a lake. It is the result of years of planning and careful design and artisanship (Ketton Stone for the facing ashlar, R.W. Armstrong builders, joinery by S.B. Joinery and plasterwork by Stevensons of Norwich).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/07.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/thumbs/07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contained quality of the exterior leads to a genuine sense of surprise inside: the house has generously scaled interiors, and tall sash windows flood the rooms with light. The main entrance hall is designed to link with a cross-axial corridor, the passage being indicated by a screen of columns, echoing the arrangements in eighteenth-century houses such as Dumfries House in Ayrshire, Scotland, behind which is an apsidal staircase compartment with a finely detailed oak staircase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/08.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/09.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The well-proportioned drawing room and billiard room, separated by double doors, fill the south front, and have fine views across the wider landscape. The long dining room, kitchen and breakfast room are situated at the east end, with other supporting spaces, including a generous inner hall and boot room, that essential space of country-house life. The breakfast room is especially attractive, with a Venetian window facing east, to enjoy the morning sun. On the first floor a long, broad axial corridor links the bedrooms, and those in the wings are also more low ceilinged, which gives them a homely feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/10.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/11.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interiors are mellow and bright, with inherited furniture from other family homes, comfortable upholstered chairs and sofas. Interior design advice was also provided by Jane Ormsby Gore, who grew up on the Welsh borders. Her father, Lord Harlech, was ambassador to the US, so she lived for a while in the famous Lutyens-designed embassy there, and has a good understanding of classical interiors; she has worked on numerous country-house interiors, from Ashdown House in Berkshire to Chilham Castle in Kent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the rooms there is an emphasis on comfort, ease of circulation and appropriateness. Colours are in an earthy natural range and pleasantly recessive, such as Naples Yellow, a primrose yellow and a soft moss green in principal rooms, where there are 
full curtains at the windows and good quality upholstered furniture with touches of Indian and Middle Eastern fabrics in the cushions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a new house in the country is a particular challenge, but here it was met with considerable thought, research and design imagination. The house forms a new chapter in the continuing history of English classical country-house design in the twenty-first century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/12.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/13.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was one of Francis Terry’s first independent projects, and combines imaginatively so many strands of the English country-house tradition with modern taste and technology. It has proved to be a happy home for his clients and their family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/14.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-wiltshire/thumbs/14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Wiltshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text adapted from Romantics &amp;amp; Classics: Style in the English Country House by Jeremy Musson, published by Rizzoli in 2021&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/house-in-wiltshire/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/house-in-wiltshire/</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>featured-projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>House in Suffolk</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/01.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house in Suffolk was an alteration and extension to a modern classical house. The original home was a five bay block with large over hanging eaves, built in the early 2000s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, Francis Terry was appointed by a new client to extend and improve the property. This presented a rare opportunity to revisit the earlier design, elevate the architecture, and create a more resolved and site-responsive composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house is constructed from buff-coloured brick, a material commonly found in Georgian architecture throughout Suffolk. This material palette was established in the original design and has been continued in the extensions and alterations, helping to ensure visual continuity and local authenticity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/05.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/06.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The redesign aimed to strengthen the classical language of the original house while introducing a greater sense of balance and proportion. Previously, a single-storey conservatory on one side and a screen wall on the other disrupted the intended symmetry of the building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key interventions by Francis Terry was to address the roof, which in the original design featured large overhanging eaves with a shallow pitch, compromising the usable living space, and a lack of windows, denying light and views across the wider landscape. Francis replaced this with a parapet and a new, steeper pitched roof punctuated by dormer windows. This alteration created a more pleasing and balanced composition while significantly improving the attic accommodation. The new roof retained the use of slate to match the original, maintaining coherence across old and new elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the original house, the whole interior was redesigned to give the property a unified composition with the new wings. This included architraves, cornices and other joinery mouldings. The original dogleg staircase was replaced with a sweeping flight, following Georgian precedents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/07.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/08.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/09.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new extensions re-establish a more ordered and harmonious composition. Designed to be symmetrical and subservient in height to the main house, the wings step gently down into the landscape, creating a soft transition between the main block and the surrounding garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Situated on rising ground with panoramic views across the surrounding countryside, the site offered the opportunity to make a bolder architectural statement. The extended house now reads as a baroque composition, with arms reaching out toward the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/10.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the west side of the house is a pool with a pool house also by Francis Terry. This is designed as a picturesque folly in the tradition of garden buildings for country houses. The front façade is a Tuscan order with a small central pediment. Further Tuscan columns frame the pool space on the side of the house, making two sides of an architectural exterior ‘room’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis Terry’s connection to the wider Suffolk region informed the practice’s thoughtful approach. Having grown up in the surrounding countryside, he has long held an understanding and appreciation of the area’s landscape character and architectural traditions. That knowledge is reflected in every aspect of the redesign. The finished house sits proudly within its landscape, offering a respectful yet distinctive contribution to the architectural heritage of the region, and serving as a testament to the enduring value of classical architecture in a contemporary context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/11.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-suffolk/thumbs/11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Suffolk&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/house-in-suffolk/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/house-in-suffolk/</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>featured-projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>House in Northamptonshire</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/01.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/thumbs/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new country house addresses the challenge of combining the traditional architectural forms of its locality with flexible and modern living spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is always a challenge to design a new house to fit well into an old landscape. A number of important factors are at play – the particular topography, the appropriate materials and the overall spirit of place. The architect Francis Terry has recently completed a new house for a family with strong equestrian interests, located in that distinctive rolling Northamptonshire landscape. It fits into its existing landscape like a glove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This handsome new house replaced an existing building of some size, which had, however, been considerably extended in different stages. Its new owners had received permission for further extensions but concluded that the resulting house would not be right. Instead, they decided to start again, retaining a reduced part of the old house as an outbuilding to the new. This, together with existing farm buildings, provided a practical context for the new work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were several false starts to the project. Happily, the clients, meeting Mr Terry almost by chance, found him able to give expression to their hopes for the site. They commissioned from him a design for a new Modern Classical house, on a dignified, square plan that allowed for both large reception rooms and other rooms of a more intimate character. The work properly began with a preliminary day of discussion and drawing, in which the architect sought to understand and articulate visually the taste, hopes and needs of his clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Terry, who has become a leading country house architect, has risen to the challenge of designing a generous new family house with the traditional character and form of a Northamptonshire smaller manor house or hunting box. Although alternatives along more neo-Palladian models were considered, as built, the final design is perhaps a little more Queen Anne in feel, with later-Georgian proportions. The best of all worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In choosing materials for the house, Mr Terry and his clients wanted to celebrate the vernacular and traditional stone detailing of buildings in the locality. The solid stone elevations are beautifully detailed with coursed ironstone rubble – quarried at Great Tew in Oxfordshire – and finely cut or ashlar blocks of limestone, in this case Bath stone from Hartham Park, Wiltshire. The house consists of two storeys with an attic, the latter enlivened with grouped dormers under segmental pediments in an early 18th-century manner, made of painted hardwood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house showed how coursed ironstone could be framed and enlivened with crisp limestone ashlar architectural elements, such as quoins, string courses, window and door surrounds. The use of high-quality limestone for architectural detailing was dictated by the fact that the local ironstone carved poorly, but also that, when used together, the two stones had an appealing aesthetic result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give variety to the composition and to mark out this modern Classical house from historic precedents, large expanses of limestone were incorporated at the centre of both the main elevations of the house to the west and east. This treatment gives them weight and an inviting presence. The mansard roof over the house, slightly French in character, is covered in natural dark-grey slate with lead dressings and rolls. Mr Terry and his associate Martyn Winney worked closely with Kingerlee of Oxford as contractors, specialists in stone masonry work. In the manner of early 18th-century buildings, the cornice is in painted timber and, as at Belton House in Lincolnshire, the timber is painted to match the stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that, despite giving an appearance of regularity and symmetry overall, each elevation is quite different, varied by the placing of windows and doors, as well as by contrasting masonry finishes. The windows are of two types. There are tripartite openings of a form more associated with the late 18th and early 19th century – and perhaps particularly with the Wyatt dynasty of late-Georgian architects and builders – as well as tall sashes. The entrance front has a central three-bay section of limestone ashlar crowned with a segmental pediment. It faces an informally planned yard of buildings that include part of the reduced former farmhouse. The entrance doorcase comprises Tuscan-Doric pillars supporting a smaller segmental pediment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/thumbs/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the west or garden front, the façade is flanked to either side by tripartite windows at ground- and first-floor level. Within the central section of the façade, there is a complex organisation of elements: three dormer windows at roof level, four first-floor sashes, and a door with flanking windows and two sashes at ground level. The door is crowned with a second segmental pediment. The overall effect is subtle and elegant, almost Gibbsian, and has an echo of the same arrangement at Newbridge in Co. Dublin, Ireland, one of Gibbs’s memorable country-house designs. This front enjoys views across open farmland towards wooded hills in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The north side has fewer windows altogether, but a centrally placed door, and, with its broad sections of coursed rubble ironstone, has a feeling of solidity that perhaps echoes more the traditional farmhouses of the region. On the south front is a projecting breakfast room with windows on three sides, finished in limestone ashlar, giving a different emphasis again. The overall effect of this variety is at once formal and informal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interior planning is similarly a mixture of traditional and modern, with a generous double-height hall, where a staircase leads to a galleried landing. The other principal rooms are arranged around this light-filled space, which can double as a reception room for larger entertainments; the modern family kitchen fills the south side of the house, whereas the main drawing room and dining room fill the rest of the west front and are interconnecting. The bedroom suites are approached from the galleried landing, which acts as a kind of axial corridor on the first floor. The mansard-style roof means there are also generous rooms within the attic storey, including a broad sitting room at its centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house is an assured and dignified composition, echoing the traditional houses of status in Northamptonshire, with all the conveniences of a fluid modern plan form and modern technology – with an emphasis on light. The house took two years to build from the granting of planning consent, and the family moved into the house in 2022; handsome and convenient, it also has all the benefits of a good set of existing outbuildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/07.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/thumbs/07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Northamptonshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interiors have been finished in a blend of traditional and contemporary style that suits the house well, including &lt;em&gt;Zoffany&lt;/em&gt; wallpaper in the drawing room, a long kitchen table by &lt;em&gt;Julian Chichester&lt;/em&gt; and a dining table and large set of late-17th-century-style chairs acquired from nearby Thorpe Mandeville Hall. &lt;em&gt;Helen Wallace Interiors&lt;/em&gt; gave advice on the decoration, &lt;em&gt;Lucy Martin&lt;/em&gt; on the lighting, and &lt;em&gt;Rebecca Bannerman&lt;/em&gt; on the exterior lighting. The gardens were laid out by garden designer &lt;em&gt;James Alexander-Sinclair&lt;/em&gt;, with planting concentrated close to the terraces on the south and west of the house; the lawns are left open to preface the fields and paddocks beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house is a good example of Mr Terry’s Modern Classical designs, which combine a solid, well-built architectural presence, expressive of materials and carefully judged Classical detail, with unexpected and cheerful variations on a theme. The architect often references the influence of the buildings at his school, &lt;em&gt;Stowe&lt;/em&gt; in Buckinghamshire, as a formative part of his aesthetic understanding: in effect, he grew up surrounded by works of William Kent, James Gibbs and Giovanni-Battista Borra. He studied architecture at Cambridge and qualified as an architect in 1994, subsequently working for 20 years with his father, Quinlan Terry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this period, the Terrys collaborated on major country-house projects, such as &lt;em&gt;Ferne Park&lt;/em&gt; in Wiltshire and &lt;em&gt;Kilboy&lt;/em&gt; in Co. Tipperary, Ireland, as well as the new infirmary building for the &lt;em&gt;Royal Hospital Chelsea&lt;/em&gt;, SW3, before Mr Terry Jnr set up his own practice in 2016. This training and experience, combined with his additional career as an award-winning artist, has given him an unusual versatility as a designer in the domestic sphere. Indeed, it is his eye as an artist that echoes the approach of certain architects of the 19th and early 20th century who could compose architecture in its landscape setting: &lt;em&gt;George Devey&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Edwin Lutyens&lt;/em&gt; were both masters of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Terry is increasingly renowned for his concept sketches and watercolours, which he executes himself. These help to communicate the evolving designs he works on, which is helpful to both client and planners. This approach was particularly valuable in this project, allowing his clients to find visual expression for their ideas. Last year, Mr Terry published &lt;em&gt;A Life in Sketchbooks&lt;/em&gt;, edited by his son Alfred, which includes selections from his architectural sketchbooks from all periods of his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well read in all the works of the great masters of Italian, English and Irish architecture, Mr Terry works successively across a range of classical and traditional styles, reflected in such projects as the new house in Hampshire. He strives to produce a design that is suitable to its setting and, at the same time, realises the dreams of his clients in terms of modern living on both large and small scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brief Mr Terry received on this project was to create a new house that would feel right for its landscape context and that would reflect all the admired qualities of the Queen Anne and Georgian house. It also allows for all the expectations of modern family life on the interior – from the bathroom suite to the boot room, with rooms to entertain and relax in – and exterior; convenient access to the stables was essential. In short, everything that is necessary for the enjoyment of modern country life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was adapted from an original published in the 24 July 2024 edition of&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Country Life&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;written by Jeremy Musson.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/house-in-northamptonshire/</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>featured-projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>House in Hampshire</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/01.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/thumbs/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of a new country house depends, in large part, on how it reads within its landscape setting, and Wield Park, near Alresford in Hampshire, designed by Francis Terry and completed in 2020, is an inspiring example of a house rooted in the history and character of its surroundings. It shows exactly what can be achieved in a project of close collaboration between a far-sighted client, an experienced architect, and a top landscape designer. At the core of its story is the revival of the landscape to designs by Christian Sweet of Colson Stone Practice. To come across its newly planted parkland, its expansive curved lake, and carefully judged parkland tree plantings is to enjoy a vision of inspired design and land management that imparts a 21st-century Reptonian thrill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/thumbs/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Wield Park, the client and the architect sought to create a home in the spirit of a Hampshire manor house of the late 17th century, but with generous modern plan forms and light and airy interiors. In this sense, we might describe Wield Park as the very essence of the &lt;em&gt;English country house revisited&lt;/em&gt; in the 21st century. The previous use of the site for intensive agricultural purposes had left a badly scarred and degraded environment, served by a modest modern brick farmhouse. For those who can remember that lost view, the transformation is almost unbelievable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/thumbs/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subtle but still confident Classicism of the house reflects Mr Terry’s experienced eye. He was educated amid the faded temples and Classical pile of Stowe School before studying architecture at Cambridge. For two decades, he worked for—latterly in partnership with—his father, Quinlan Terry, champion of the tradition of Classical architecture. They collaborated on important new country houses, such as Ferne Park in Dorset and Kilboy in Ireland. He set up his own practice, Francis Terry &amp;amp; Associates, in 2016 and is well established as a leading country-house architect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Terry describes his approach as an ‘intuitive’ response to place, as well as to the character of his clients, noting how often childhood homes become part of the discussion with clients about the houses in which they want to live and raise their own families. Mr Terry studied painting and has exhibited at the Royal Academy, an element that brings an additional quality to his design processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His ‘skill in drawing and the handling of light and shadow’ was noted by the late Prof. David Watkin in his 2015 book &lt;em&gt;The Practice of Classical Architecture: The Architecture of Quinlan and Francis Terry, 2005–2015.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Wield Park, the project’s collaborative approach included advice from Rural Solutions to obtain planning, and work by Alex Jaggs, head of the team at Finchatton, which delivered to the highest level on the construction and all aspects of the interior. The author of this article was also involved on the project as an expert design reviewer. From the start, the design aimed to be what is described with reference to planning legislation as a ‘Paragraph 80e’ house, defined by the National Planning Policy Framework. That is to say, it would show exceptional design quality rooted in the characteristics of local buildings. Without deviating from that aim, planning permission was, in fact, ultimately granted under the replacement-dwelling policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/05.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/thumbs/05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result bears witness to a highly considered programme of work. It reflects the beauty of building in a traditional style, yet incorporates a contemporary version of family life, expressed in a fluid, open interior plan and generous bedroom spaces. The design of the house was informed by a full survey of local historic architecture—both polite and vernacular—and the typical well-ordered elevations that characterise so many of the country houses of Hampshire, from the mid-17th to early 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of ‘classical continuity’, it is interesting to reflect how this house can be linked to the principal country house in the near vicinity, Moundsmere Manor, which was designed by Sir Reginald Blomfield and built in 1908–09 in an ambitious late-17th-century or neo-Wren style. Blomfield, who wrote &lt;em&gt;The Formal Garden in England&lt;/em&gt; (1892), also laid out the gardens there and the estate features a pair of lodges in a simplified neo-Georgian style. Other Arts-and-Crafts and Classical-inspired houses that became part of the design conversation include nearby Marsh Court by Edwin Lutyens—a dramatic clunch-built house on a sloping site near Stockbridge, constructed for the investor Herbert Johnson in 1901–04—and Lutyens’s stone-built Middleton Park in Oxfordshire, created in the 1930s for the Earl of Jersey and his American countess. Airy 1920s Long Island houses, combining English and French influences, with their notably generous scale and fluid plans, also played a part in discussions about the evolving design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precise positioning of the new house is a crucial factor in its success. The modern farmhouse that previously stood on the site was located higher up the slope and on the same level of the ancient woodland, whereas the new site was chosen to be lower. Therefore, the new house is sheltered in the contours of the landscape and allows views to the north-west, without breaking into the well-established tree line. This allows for a more private, terraced garden area south of the principal range, created to designs by Mr Sweet, and for the parkland to sweep up to the house to the north and west. There was a strong sense that the building should gracefully ornament the survived landscape—not dominate it—but give it a pleasing visual focus. Mr Sweet took inspiration from major examples of Humphry Repton’s work for the way they engage with their surroundings to develop a new plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having studied landscape architecture at Thames Polytechnic, Mr Sweet is partnered by his wife, Debbie, at Colson Stone Practice. Based in Somerset since 2005, their work on historic gardens and landscapes includes Endsleigh in Devon, Caerhays Castle in Cornwall, and Kenwood House in north London—all places strongly associated with Repton. Their work on Villa Balbiano on Lake Como, Italy, won the Society of Garden Designers’ Historic Restoration Award. Their projects are always rooted in an understanding of the history of each landscape setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Wield Park sits comfortably into its setting is partly the result of the overall shape of the house and its building materials. Wield Park’s service wing and lower buildings to the west are built of traditional Hampshire red brick, with clay tile roofs. By contrast, the main house is constructed from pale but warm Yorkshire limestone, from quarries operated by Cadeby Stone, which Mr Terry regards as a highly versatile stone for building. This manages to echo the local clunch-building tradition in a more durable form and references the grander Hampshire houses of the later 17th century, such as Wolvesey Palace in Winchester. Traditional grey slate has been used for the main roofs, which are punctuated by dormers with segmental pediments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main entrance elevation is broken up by a central recession of three bays between shallow one-bay projections in the late-17th-century manner. Although echoing Lainston House, near Winchester, this is also reminiscent of Repton’s Sheringham Hall in Norfolk, which gave the inspiration for the long porch supported by simple, paired Tuscan columns. The single-storey canted bay windows on each of the external bays offer expansive views across the park and provide balconies to the bedrooms above, where Serliana windows add a bold Palladian touch. On the western garden elevation, there is a striking contrast of material between the stone elevations and brick chimney stacks. The south-facing façade repeats the overall design of the entrance side, but its views engage with the formal garden terraces and lawn, looking up to the ancient woodland above. The different play of light gives the façade a contrasting feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/06.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/07.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internally, the plan creates a splendid interior enfilade from the ‘everyday’ entrance to the west, where the service range is clustered with a guest cottage and garaging to form something like a traditional stable yard. The long enfilade begins in the service range and leads past the kitchen—an ingenious galleried design that evokes something of the interior of a yacht—a dining room and sitting room, then beyond through the double-height, south-facing staircase hall, into the light and airy principal drawing room to the east.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first floor has a similar long, broad corridor connecting bedrooms and bathrooms; the principal bedrooms enjoying floor-to-ceiling views from the Serliana windows. Above this, attic-level bedrooms form enjoyably eccentric spaces, rather like spacious tent rooms within the roof pitch and given further depth by the dormers. Some of the most engaging moments of the house are unexpected glimpses between interior and exterior; for instance, the glimpse from the staircase hall of the first-floor oval windows on the return of the projecting bays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/08.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/thumbs/08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early discussions about the landscape, Mr Sweet presented the client with an image taken from Repton’s &lt;em&gt;Red Book&lt;/em&gt; for Kenwood, showing a view across the bathing ponds, with a low bridge, sinuous drive, and dense woodland beyond. This helped determine the overall concept for Wield Park. One third of the 370-acre site consisted of ancient woodland, all now under a management plan to enhance its ecological diversity. The new landscaping is, like the house itself, subtle and bold; it is carefully graduated, and the park designed as grazed pasture in the local tradition. The scale of the operation needs to be recognised: six acres of new trees have been added to the ancient woodland, together with 300 individual parkland trees in shaped groups throughout the new parkland—mainly oak, but with beech, sweet chestnut, lime, some cedars, and London plane. A total of six acres of new water has been introduced in a sequence of lakes and ponds following the valley bed, as well as hedgerows of mixed hawthorn, blackthorn, cornus, and holly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, this rich landscape enhancement of the house is the final touch to complete the poetic transformation of this formerly degraded agricultural property into a dream country house in the English spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/09.jpg&quot; title=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/house-in-hampshire/09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Hampshire&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adapted from Country Life article, July 26, 2023, by Jeremy Musson.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/house-in-hampshire/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/house-in-hampshire/</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>featured-projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Castle Howard</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-19.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-19.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-20.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-03b.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-03b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Tapestry Drawing Room at Castle Howard is a completely new architectural treatment to a room which was destroyed by fire in 1940. The room had been left as an empty shell of charred stonework ever since. The brief was to restore the room to what Vanbrugh would have done and incorporate the four Vanderbank tapestries which were designed and woven for the room in 1706.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-05.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The architect Francis Terry worked in collaboration with interior designers Alec Cobbe and Remy Renzullo to realise this vision. The focus of the design is a baroque chimneypiece made from scagliola with an elaborate overmantel, framing a painting of the ‘Judgement of Paris’. A large entablature crowns the room with a decorative rinceau design in the frieze. The two doors have overdoor paintings depicting the life of Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-06.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-07.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Care has been taken to use traditional materials and techniques where possible. All architectural elements of the project were hand drawn by Francis Terry at full size.  Unusually, the room uses onsite run plasterwork made in the traditional way, rather than fibrous plaster made off site which is conventionally used. The frieze of the fireplace has a head of Pluto framed by a cartouche which was carved by hand from limewood. The room is painted a dark blue to bring out the colours of the much-faded tapestries. In keeping with the baroque spirit, the decoration is extensively gilded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-08.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-09.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/drawings/cabinet_room_03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Full size Cartouche. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard. Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/drawings/thumbs/cabinet_room_03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full size Cartouche. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard. Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/drawings/cabinet_room_01.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Full size Entablature. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard.  Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/drawings/thumbs/cabinet_room_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full size Entablature. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard.  Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/drawings/cabinet_room_02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Full size Swag. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard.  Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/drawings/thumbs/cabinet_room_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full size Swag. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard.  Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything in the room, apart from the antiques, paintings, and tapestries, was made in the UK within the past eighteen months. The crafts used for this room include: - hand carved timber classical ornament, traditional run plasterwork, scagliola manufacture and gilding. The craftsmanship is truly outstanding, and it is a joy to see that the UK is still world leaders in these fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-10.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-11.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-12.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-13.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-14.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-15.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour North Elevation Amended&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour North Elevation Amended&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-16.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour South Elevation Amended&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-16.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour South Elevation Amended&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-17.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour East Elevation Amended&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour East Elevation Amended&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-18.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour West Elevation Amended&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour West Elevation Amended&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/castle-howard/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/projects/castle-howard/</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>featured-projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Five Classical Orders</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;videoWrapper&quot;&gt;
	&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tKX4l6F2i5U&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proportions and defining features of the five orders of columns are a fundamental part of classical architecture. In this video, Francis and his father Quinlan Terry CBE delve deep into this cornerstone of the profession. From the rustic undecorated Tuscan order to the detailed and ornate Composite, they reflect on their usage over the years, their rich symbolism as well as the mysterious question of their distant origins.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/the-five-classical-orders/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/the-five-classical-orders/</guid>
        
        
        <category>videos</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-19.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-19.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-20.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-03b.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-03b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Tapestry Drawing Room at Castle Howard is a completely new architectural treatment to a room which was destroyed by fire in 1940. The room had been left as an empty shell of charred stonework ever since. The brief was to restore the room to what Vanbrugh would have done and incorporate the four Vanderbank tapestries which were designed and woven for the room in 1706.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-04.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-05.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The architect Francis Terry worked in collaboration with interior designers Alec Cobbe and Remy Renzullo to realise this vision. The focus of the design is a baroque chimneypiece made from scagliola with an elaborate overmantel, framing a painting of the ‘Judgement of Paris’. A large entablature crowns the room with a decorative rinceau design in the frieze. The two doors have overdoor paintings depicting the life of Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-06.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-07.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Care has been taken to use traditional materials and techniques where possible. All architectural elements of the project were hand drawn by Francis Terry at full size.  Unusually, the room uses onsite run plasterwork made in the traditional way, rather than fibrous plaster made off site which is conventionally used. The frieze of the fireplace has a head of Pluto framed by a cartouche which was carved by hand from limewood. The room is painted a dark blue to bring out the colours of the much-faded tapestries. In keeping with the baroque spirit, the decoration is extensively gilded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-08.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-09.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/drawings/cabinet_room_03.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Full size Cartouche. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard. Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/drawings/thumbs/cabinet_room_03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full size Cartouche. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard. Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/drawings/cabinet_room_01.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Full size Entablature. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard.  Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/drawings/thumbs/cabinet_room_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full size Entablature. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard.  Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/drawings/cabinet_room_02.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Full size Swag. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard.  Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/images/drawings/thumbs/cabinet_room_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full size Swag. Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard.  Drawn by Francis Terry 2023&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything in the room, apart from the antiques, paintings, and tapestries, was made in the UK within the past eighteen months. The crafts used for this room include: - hand carved timber classical ornament, traditional run plasterwork, scagliola manufacture and gilding. The craftsmanship is truly outstanding, and it is a joy to see that the UK is still world leaders in these fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-10.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-11.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-12.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-13.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-14.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New Tapestry Drawing Room, Castle Howard is Completed&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-15.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour North Elevation Amended&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour North Elevation Amended&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-16.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour South Elevation Amended&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-16.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour South Elevation Amended&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-17.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour East Elevation Amended&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour East Elevation Amended&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2025/CHDR-18.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour West Elevation Amended&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2025/thumbs/CHDR-18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castle Howard Watercolour West Elevation Amended&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/new-tapestry-drawing-room-castle-howard/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/new-tapestry-drawing-room-castle-howard/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quinlan Terry's Life in Architecture</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;videoWrapper&quot;&gt;
	&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Zr9Z1rpsfek&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video is an interview between Francis and his father Quinlan Terry CBE, discussing the many unforgettable moments in his highly successful sixty-year career. His life has seen classical and traditional architecture change from being derided as a joke and even immoral in the ‘50s and ‘60s, to its adoption by Prince Charles and the Post-Modern movement in the ‘80s, and now its total acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as an investigation into these broad cultural trends, Quinlan recounts many of the amusing anecdotes that punctuated his career: these include, working with Profumo during the scandal, collaborating with Sir Anthony Blunt on researching Renaissance architecture, and being in Libya measuring Roman ruins at the time of the Gaddafi coup d’état.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a broad variety of topics discussed, this interview will interest architects and non-architects alike.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/quinlan-terrys-life-in-architecture/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/thoughts/quinlan-terrys-life-in-architecture/</guid>
        
        
        <category>videos</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted</title>
        <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/hans-place-12-24.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/hans-place-12-24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to be part of a team which have been granted planning consent for a new seven unit apartment scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge. The new building replaces a modernist style house built in the 1960s, which is unsympathetic to the area both in terms of materials and architectural language. The new design follows the dominant style of the square which consists of highly ornate red brick facades with brown stone and terracotta elements, using a classical style borrowed from diverse sources, including 17th century Dutch and Queen Anne influences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/hans-place-12-24-3.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/hans-place-12-24-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a class=&quot;fancybox&quot; rel=&quot;group&quot; href=&quot;/images/news/2024/hans-place-12-24-2.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot;&gt;
			&lt;img src=&quot;/images/news/2024/thumbs/hans-place-12-24-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Planning Permission for a New Seven Unit Apartment Scheme in Hans Place, Knightsbridge Has Been Granted&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-hans-place-knightsbridge/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ftanda.co.uk/news/planning-permission-hans-place-knightsbridge/</guid>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
